GREGOR KICZALES: Here's the rubric for this week.
We'll start with criteria 1 and 2 from the rubric.
What I did was I copied a solution out of edX
and pasted it into DrRacket and typed Command-I on the Macintosh
to fix the indentation.
That would be Control-I on a Windows machine.
Now, I'll just go through.
The first question is, "Is the program safe?"
It needs to be set to Beginning Student.
Now, you can't really assess that because when you copied it out of edX,
you don't know what the file was set, but you yourself
should know that the file has to be in Beginning Student.
"Does it have any requires?"
For checking that, in order to really check it properly, what I'm going to do
is, I'm going to search to see if there's
a require anywhere in the program.
You can type Command-F, you could type Control-F on Windows,
and look for certain require, and I don't find any.
So this program meets the safety criteria, and it is acceptable.
Now, let's abort this search and go on to whether it is commit ready.
Is it commit ready?
The file needs to be neat and tidy.
Let's see, that looks pretty neat and tidy to me.
I don't see stuff that's not supposed to be here.
I don't see a bunch of commented-out code.
I don't see notes to your friends.
It all looks pretty good this way.
I'm happy with that.
The thing about the indentation should conform to course conventions. , ,
Again, if you've copied it out a bracket, you can't test that,
but you could test your original file, and it should.
Basically, typing Command-I at this point shouldn't move anything.
So that gets us to a good for commit ready.
This program is off to a great start.
I'm now going to go into parts 3 and 4 of the rubric having
to do with whether the designs are complete and high quality.
In order to do that, what I'm going to do is focus here on just problem 4.
That's called spot grading where you just look at part of it.
And that's all you're going to have to do for your assessment.
You probably want to do the assessment for your whole design,
just for your own edification, but for the self-assessment part that you type
into the system, just do problem 4.
First, we need to do completeness and well-formedness.
A data definition has all of these parts.
There's the type comment.
There is the interpretation.
There's examples.
They all are there, and they look well-formed.
Here's the template.
There's the template rules used.
But if you notice carefully here something, watch this.
What if I uncomment the template and now run the file.
Now I'm going to get an error that this n is not
defined because that n should be an h.
This template is not well-formed.
It never ran.
Somebody typed # ; in front of it before they ever run it.
You gotta run it first to make sure it's well-formed.
Let's try it now.
That's better.
We'll comment it out.
The whole data definition is complete and well-formed
except for the template, which has a small problem with it.
When we look at the function design, signature
looks good, well-formed purpose, examples, there's the stub,
there's the template, and there is increased health.
You know this template could actually just be took template from health.
We'd rather do it that way.
You know, we won't ding that.
Let's just say there's one problem in the completeness
and well-formedness of the design, which is just the template.
So we will give this a fair for completeness.
Now let's go on to correctness.
Again, we need to check the correctness of all the different parts of the two
designs.
So working through here in terms of the type comment,
correctness of a type comment is "Does it
capture the information it's supposed to?"
If we go look at the problem statement, it says the only thing
that matters about their health is either they're dead,
or if they're alive, they have zero or more extra lives.
So this is clearly a one-of.
It's a one-of of a distinct.
They're dead or an interval of integers or natural numbers.
So let's see, does the type comment do that?
Yes, it's a one-of.
There is the distinct dead, and natural is good for the interval,
so that's great.
That's correct.
There are other options that could be correct.
You could use false for the dead or you could use not alive for the dead.
There's various different ways that you could do this, all of which
would be fine as long as you're capturing that information.
The interpretation is good.
It tells me what that means.
It tells me what the number means, and in any itemization,
you want examples of all the cases, and we've got that here.
So that's good and correct.
There's the template, and the template rules used.
Now is there's another little problem with this template, which
is that the order of the subclasses here is not
the same order as in the template, and we really
would like those to be in the same order.
Consistency is the hobgoblin of little minds.
Maybe I have a little mind, but I like to have them be in the same order.
I'm going to switch this to string to make that be the first case.
I'll switch these two here in the rules used.
I'll change those curlies to square brackets.
You might call all of those details, but there's
one of these that isn't a detail.
In the case of the distinct, then the question answer
is just the three parens inside the three dots inside of parens.
But in the case of the non-distinct, the question answer has to be that.
That is a real problem with the way the template is built up.
It's the only real problem.
The other ones were kind of small, but we really
do want them to be in the same order, please.
So there we go.
We've got a data definition which is mostly correct,
but there's some problems with the template.
Let's look at the function design.
It consumes health and produces health.
That's what it's supposed to do, so that's good.
And increases the number of lives for the player with one,
except when the player is already dead.
I think I know what that means.
That means if the player is alive, then it increases the number of lives.
I could leave it that way.
I could maybe improve it a little bit by just saying
increases the number of lives if the player this is alive.
That's a little bit cleaner, but the other was fine.
I might put these tests in this order again so they match the type comment,
but that truly is a detail.
There's the stub.
There is the template.
There's this.
Now I really want this to match the template that I improved.
Let's take the template up here and redo it.
We'll rename the function, and in the case where it's a string,
it doesn't change the string.
It produces dead every time, and otherwise it adds one to the health.
That's the same as this but flipped around in the new order.
We'll run it to check the tests.
There was a problem with the template up here.
Once we fix that, this down here had to change.
We don't ding twice.
We'll do a deduction because the template had a problem.
We won't do a deduction here.
We improve the grammar of this.
That's not going to count.
So this one problem here will give the quality here a good.
Now, the final element of the rubric is "Does the design
satisfy the problem requirements?"
In some sense, we've already made this clear to ourselves.
The data design does capture what it's supposed to capture.
The health has the properties it needs to have.
Because the interpretation and the type comment match up,
the date design has done the thing that it's supposed to do.
The function design is supposed to allow us
to increase the lives of a character, but it should only
do it if the character is not dead.
That is what this function does, increases the number
of lives that the player is alive.
That's the same thing as saying they're not dead.
The check expects clearly check that, so this design clearly
satisfies the problem requirements in both the data definition
and the function.
So this gets a good for satisfying problem requirements.
Now very quickly, let me just show you one other solution
so you'll see some variation that could also be a valid solution.
Here is another data definition for health.
This one uses false.
I already said that was a reasonable thing to do.
I really want to look at the function here.
Look, this function is going to take two arguments.
It takes a health and the number of lives to add.
So it adds not just one additional lives but any number of additional lives.
We didn't explicitly say that you needed to do this,
but we also didn't explicitly say that it only adds one.
So this is a completely reasonable design for this function.
The signature is correct for this alternative design.
The purpose is correct for this alternative design.
There are tests that test adding different number of lives.
The tests are good.
There's the stub.
There should be a note here about the template, but other than that,
this is a very high quality and correct solution to this slightly different
problem statement.
Totally good if you did this too, except you really
should have had a template comment here.
So that's it for this week's self-assessment video.
You've seen how we apply the rubric to both a data
design and a function design.
You should do this now with your design.
Remember, your design doesn't have to be exactly
like what we showed in the video.
You're applying the rubric in assessing whether the design is good.
You could have a different design than ours and still be good.
So there you go.
Do the self-assessment of your work, and hopefully that
will help you improve your ability to use the recipes to design.