GREGOR KICZALES: So there's my examples.
Now we'll set up to do the template.
Define fn-for-countdown c.
They'll be somebody template rules used.
So now we have to go find the first template rule used.
And again we always start by looking at the word right
after is in the type comment.
And that word is one of.
So if we go find the template rules page,
again we can find that by following this link,
the data driven templates recipe link-- The one of role
is the rule we're going to use this because this is an itemization.
The one of role is also what we used for enumerations,
so we know how it starts out.
It's going to tell us to make a cond with one
clause per subclass of the one of.
So I'll go back over to the code now, and I'll say cond
and there's three subclasses.
So there'll be three question answer pairs.
And I'll say that the rule that I used was one of three cases.
OK, so now I go to the first case.
The first case is false.
Well false is an atomic distinct value.
And I need a predicate for the question that tests for false.
It turns out there is a predicate that tests whether a value is exactly false.
So back at the code I could put that predicate,
and I can say false question mark c.
This is atomic distinct so dot dot dot.
Atomic distinct false.
So now for the second sub case, so let's see, this is an interval.
So going back to the data templates page, for interval I
need an appropriate predicate.
So this is a predicate that for example tells
me is it a number between one and 10.
But I have to be a little careful here.
If I just make this predicate be and one is less than or equal to C,
and C is less than or equal to 10, and let
me just do the answer clause quickly so we'll have that out of way.
Since this is an atomic non-distinct, this would be dot dot dot c.
That might be what you write, but this particular itemization
is called a mixed data itemization.
It's a mixed date itemization because there's different kinds of data in it.
Not all three clauses are numbers.
The first clause, the data is a boolean, the second clause it's a number,
in the third it's a string.
So I have to be very careful here.
Because if I call this template with c being the string complete, this less
than or equal right here, this less than or equal is going to blow up.
Because you can't call less than or equal giving it
a string as an argument.
So because this is a mixed data itemization,
we have to guard this less than or equal against being called
with a value that isn't a number.
The way we're going to guard it is we're going to say well,
you're only this middle case if you're a number
and you are a number between one and 10.
So I'm going to add one more test to the and.
So now if I call fun for countdown with false this template will go there.
If I call fun for countdown with a number that's between one and 10,
this template will go there.
So now I've done the the code properly, and I need
to add the template role that I used.
Atomic non distinct and it's this interval right here.
I'll just copy it.
Now going back over to the data templates page
there's a note here that says it is permissible to use else
for the last question for itemization's and large enumerations.
This is an itemization.
So we're allowed to use else for the last question.
What that means is, right here for this question I'm allowed to put else.
I don't have to put a question that tests whether C is actually
the string complete.
Let me do the answer quickly.
This complete is an atomic distinct, so the answer's going to be that.
Now let me talk about why I'm allowed to put this else here,
and it's really important.
In this course, if you have written a well formed type
comment like countdown, and you later say
that a function consumes a countdown, then you
can count on the function being called with a legal countdown.
So what that means is when this template runs in some specific function,
if C isn't false, and C isn't a number between one and 10,
then C is guaranteed to be the string complete.
You don't have to actually test here whether C is the string complete.
What we're saying is that having taken the trouble to do type comment,
and having taken the trouble to specify the signature of a function,
you can count on that being respected.
The reason that's a reasonable thing to do in this course
is the other programming languages that you will use
is a part of the programming language implementation call
the compiler, which will actually enforce that rule
to make sure that it's always true.
So it's a reasonable rule for you to start counting on here.
So now that I've done this last case I do
need to go and add my template rule used, which is atomic distinct.
And it's this complete here.
So let's see, I'll run it to make sure everything's well formed.
I don't get any errors, so it is well formed.
And I will comment out that piece of it.
Save the file.
And now, I've got the data definition for this countdown type.