GREGOR KICZALES: So far, you've seen how to write
expressions that operate on numbers.
And you've learned the primitive call rule for evaluating those expressions.
But numbers aren't the only primitive kind of data in Racket.
In this video, we're going to learn about strings,
which are used to represent words and names,
and images, which let us start to build up pictures.
We won't have to learn any new evaluation rules, though,
because calls to string and image primitives
work just like calls to number primitives.
So even though this video is a little bit long,
I think you'll find it moves along quite quickly.
First, we'll look at string primitives.
Then we'll look at some image primitives.
There's one tricky part having to do with the way we number
the characters in a string.
But I plan to spend a couple minutes on that,
just to be sure to show you how it works.
In the beginning student language, strings look like this.
There's a double quote and then some characters,
like apple, and then another double quote.
And Racket highlights the string between the quotes with green for us
to help us see it.
So that's a string.
Here's another string, Ada, someone's name, and strings are values.
So if we run the program with these two strings in it, the value of the strings
is the strings themselves.
So apple produces apple and Ada produces Ada.
Now what are some things we can do with strings?
Well, one things we could do with strings is put them together.
So let's say we have two strings, Ada, which is someone's first name,
and Lovelace, which is someone's last name, we can put them together
like that.
And if we run that, string append is an operation, kind of like plus,
but for strings.
It glues the two strings together like that.
And probably, if it's somebody's name, we
might want to put another space in there.
And one way to do that would be to just add a third argument to string
append that adds the extra space in there.
And there we go.
And there we get Ada Lovelace-- who you might want to look up.
She's very famous for computer scientists.
In the 1840s, the 1840s, she wrote the first computer program ever written.
It was written for a machine which, at the time, only existed on paper.
The machine itself didn't run until quite recently,
but she wrote the program in the 1840s.
So that's one thing we can do with strings.
We've got strings.
We can put strings together like that.
Let me just point out one little wrinkle about strings.
This is a string.
That is a string that happens to have the characters 1, 2, and 3 in it.
And this is a number, 123.
And they're not the same.
So, in particular, you could take the number and add 1 to it.
If we run that program, get 124 as the result of that expression.
But you can't take the string and add 1 to it.
If you try to do that, you'll get this error message.
Plus expects a number as its second argument.
You gave it a string.
And Racket nicely highlights, for us, where the error is.
And you'll probably make this mistake.
Everybody makes it at first when they're learning the difference between strings
and numbers.
And you just look at that, and you say, oh, I meant this to be a number.
And you just get rid of those string quotes.
And now this program does run.
And both of those are working.
We get 124 twice.
OK, let me show you two more primitives on strings very quickly.
What I'll do is I'll delete that stuff.
And I'll comment this stuff out.
The one operation we can do on strings is to take string length, for example,
of apple.
And string-length is a primitive which tells us how long a string is.
And that string is, let's see, a-p-p-l-e, five characters,
sure enough.
So that's one thing we could do with strings.
There's another operation we have called substring.
And substring is going to let us take out parts of the string.
So if, for example, we have a string like caribou,
substring lets us take out parts of the string.
Let me just give you an example here.
If I say caribou 2 and 4, that's going to mean take out
all the characters from 2 to 4.
Give us just those characters.
Now, that's ri.
And the question is, why is that ri?
Well, there's a funny little trick here that computer scientists
have played on the world, which is to use something
called the zero-based indexing.
And in order to understand zero-based indexing, the way I always do it is I
make myself a string that looks like this.
I make a little string that's 012345678--
that's probably long enough for now.
And what zero-based indexing means is it means that, for substring,
if we operate in this string here, 012345678-- and we go from 2 to 4,
it means start at character number 2 in zero-based indexing and go right up
to, but not including, character number 4 in zero-based indexing.
So again, if you take this, what I'll do is I'll take this string here,
and I'll line it up perfectly with caribou.
And now you can see why we get ri-- because r starts at 2.
And we end right before 4.
So that's the trick of zero-based indexing.
And a lot of people make mistakes about this.
They get what are called off by one errors
because they confuse the zero-based indexing.
Again, don't worry about it if that happens.
One of the great things about computer programming
is these machines are not fragile.
If you make a mistake, you get an error message,
not quite the right thing happens, you just fix it.
I'm not saying we shouldn't worry about errors in our programs.
The design method we're going to learn is
going to help us prevent and find such errors.
All I'm saying is, if you get an error while you are working,
don't worry about it.
Look at the error message and fix the problem.
So just so you see one other example of substring,
let's say if I say substring of caribou, and I
want just the first three characters, I would say 0, and I'll stop at 3.
And that gives me the car.