GREGOR KICZALES: Here's another how to design data problem.
In this case, it's going to be for an enumeration.
So the data definition that we produce will
be similar to the TrafficLightColor example from earlier in the week.
This is the problem in letter-grade-starter.rkt.
And again, I know that this is a data design problem,
so I've got the how to design data recipe here.
And I've got the how to design data web page open in my browser here.
We're designing a system to keep track of student grades.
And we need to design a data definition to represent the letter
grade in a course, which is one of A, B, or C.
Now, the key thing about the information in this problem
is that there's three distinct values.
In other words, every letter grade is going
to be either the distinct value A or the distinct value B
or the distinct value C. It isn't like something where
we might be keeping track of the numerical score
in a course, which is a whole bunch of numbers.
Here, there's really a modest number of distinct values A, B, or C.
And when the problem domain information is
like that, when it consists of a fixed number of distinct values,
then there's a special kind of data definition
to use for that called an enumeration.
And the way an enumeration works is that we're
going to use one of in the type comment this way.
Now, this is exactly like the traffic light data
definition from earlier this week.
So here we go.
I'm going to say letter grade is one of.
And now what I'm going to do is I'm going
to talk about the data used to represent each of the distinct cases.
And I'll use strings in this case.
I'll say that these are the three distinct data
values, which are going to represent the three distinct information values.
And when you do an enumeration, the interpretation
tends to be relatively straightforward.
In this case, you'll just say the letter grade in a course.
But if you think back to that example we saw at the beginning of the week,
if for example you had decided to use the three data values,
maybe numbers like 0, 1, and 2, well then your interpretation
would be more substantive.
Then your interpretation would have to say something
like zero means A, 1 means B, 2 means C. So part
of why the interpretation is simple in this case
is because we're using strings to represent the three cases.
And the strings so clearly say what the cases are.
The other thing that happens in enumerations
is that examples are silly.
If we tried to write examples for this, what would we write?
We'd write some like define letter grade 1 is A. Means A. Define letter grade 2
is B. Means B. Define letter grade 3 is C means C. it's silly, right?
It's ridiculous.
Because it's an enumeration, there's only three values.
We know what the examples are before we get to the example stage.
So we don't even bother to write them.
What we write here is we say examples are redundant for enumerations.
And once we get a couple weeks farther in the course,
you don't even have to write that.
We want to write it for now just as a way of remembering
that the example step existed.
Now we're going to do the template.
So define fn-for-letter-grade lg is going to be some body here.
Template rules used.
And here we go.
I'll go back over to the how to design data web page.
Here we were.
And I'll scroll up to find the link to the data driven templates recipe.
And here we go.
So I need to look in this column for the first word after is.
Now remember, the first word after is is one of.
So it's not any of these.
There's a special rule for one of.
And one ofs are always enumerations, like this case is,
or an itemization, which is the example we'll do after this.
And now this says that the body is a cond with one
clause per subclass of the one of.
What does that mean?
What's a subclass of the one of?
Well, what's going on here in this one of
is there's three cases or three subclasses.
This says every letter grade in the world
is either in this class, in this class, or in this class.
Every letter grade in the world is either an A, a B, or a C.
So here we go.
It says that we're going to make a cond with one
clause per subclass of the one of.
So let me just do that.
I'm going to say cond.
And there's going to be three of these.
Because there's three there, so there will be three here.
And down here in my template rules, I'm going
to put that we use the one of rule and that there are three cases.
Now what happens?
Well, now I've gotten past the one of.
And the next thing I see is an A. The next thing I see, in fact,
is the string A.
So which template rule is that?
Because what this says is that for each question and answer expression,
I'm going to form it by following the rule in the question or answer
column of this table for the corresponding case.
So I'm going to this a.
And I need to find its row in this table.
And a is an atomic, distinct value.
Now you understand what the distinct value rule that we were just
skipping over before was.
There's a single value, the string a.
So it's this case.
And now you also understand what the cond question column of this table
was for.
It says that in the question column, we're
going to put the appropriate predicate, which is a string equal in this case.
So we'll go back over here.
And we'll say string=?
letter grade to A.
That's the question.
And in the cond answer, we're going to put just dot dot dot.
Now, you might ask, why aren't we putting dot dot dot letter grade?
Well, two answers.
One answer is the table told us to put just dot dot dot.
It didn't tell us to put dot, dot, dot in the name of the parameter.
It told us to just put dot, dot, dot.
But the question is, why does the table say that?
Well, the table says that because in this case, we know what lg is.
Lg is the string A. It'll always be the string A if we get to this cond answer.
So we're not putting it there to make that more clear.
And so the template that we used here was atomic distinct value A.
Now we go onto the next row.
Well, the next row is the string B. So we could go back to the table.
Let's see.
The string B is an atomic distinct value.
So the cond question will be an appropriate predicate.
And the cond answer will be open paren dot dot dot closed round bracket.
So let's see the cond question.
It's string=?
letter grade to B. And the cond answer is dot dot dot.
And this is atomic distinct value B. And at this point,
you can see how this is working.
And you can short circuit the process of doing C a bit if you want.
We'll just copy the case for B. We'll get rid
of this last question answer pair.
We'll make that be C. And we can do that down here in the template rules
as well.
Now we'll run it.
There's no errors.
So it's all well formed.
We'll comment that out.
So this is an enumeration because the domain information here
has two or more distinct values.
A, B, and C. And an enumeration data definition
uses a one of with the data values that are
going to be used to represent the information.
And now we've seen two new template rules.
The one of rule and the distinct value rule.
So there we go.
That's our data definition for LetterGrade.