GREGOR KICZALES: Here's another sample how to design functions problem.
In this problem, we're going to see a few extra wrinkles; including
an example of how not to write a good purpose,
some problems that can come up with tests,
and some issues having to do with copying part of what's in the template.
OK, so here's the example, I'm going to design a function called
area that consumes the length of one side of a square
and produces the area of the square.
Let's see, so the length is going to be a number, and the area of a square
is also going to be a number.
So the signature is number to number.
And the purpose is given length of one side of square produce
the area of the square.
Let me just make a note here about what's not a good purpose.
This is not a good purpose.
Given number, produce number.
That just repeats the signature.
That's not telling me something we don't already know.
The purpose needs to tell me something more specific
than the signature about exactly what we do with the given number
and exactly what the number we produce means.
Given the length of one side of the square,
it says this is the length of one side of the square,
produce the area of the square.
This number is going to be the area of the square.
So that's what we want a purpose statement to do
is be quite specific about what's going on.
So now, let's see, the stub is define area.
This is a one-argument function.
And maybe the length of a side will be s.
We can use any name we want, but s seems good.
And, let's see, this is producing a number,
so a good dummy value to produce is 0.
Now let's do some check-expects.
Let's see, check-expect area of 3.
Well, if one side of the square is 3, then the area is 9.
We'll do another one, check-expect area of, let's say, 3.2.
And, let's see, the area of that square is times 3.2,
3.2-- I won't try to do that in my head.
Now we run the check-expects.
And both ran, they failed, but they both ran, so that means they're well-formed.
We can continue.
Now, let's see, we've got the stub.
Let's comment out the stub and label it, and we'll write the template.
Area with a parameter s that's number, the template is . . .
s.
And it's going to be good to have a copy of that template,
so I'll make a copy of it right there.
We'll comment out the original template, we'll label it as the original.
And now, let's see, if this is a function that consumes the side
and it just multiplies this side by itself, so this becomes times s s.
Let's run that.
We've got a failing test here, let's see what's happening.
This says that the actual value 9 differs from 3, the expected value.
And I can click to see which test it is.
It said it produced 9 and; oh, here's a thing that happens,
this test is actually wrong.
That's not supposed to be 3, that's supposed to be 9.
Now if we run it, both tests pass.
So there's two interesting things in this example,
one is to note that you need to be careful if you get a failing test
to make sure the test is right.
If your test is wrong and you make the function conform to it,
then the function will be wrong.
And that happens, sometimes you write a test
and you're just going a bit too quickly and you put the wrong expected value.
So whenever you have a failing test, first
look at the test to see if the test is right.
The second interesting thing that's happening in this example
is to see that sometimes you have to copy part of the template.
Remember the template for this function was dot dot dot s.
In the final function we ended up with s times s.
So we copied a piece of the template, and that's OK.
The template is really trying to tell you;
hey, here's the stuff you have to work with.
You can use it in any way you want, it's just
telling you this is the parts list, you can use s twice.
So there you go, that's our second function.
I'll save it, run it one more time.