GREGOR KICZALES: In this video, I'm going
to step back from the details of the functions operating on lists
that we've been designing and give you a more abstract way of looking
at those functions.
Now, what do I mean when I say abstract?
Well, I mean a view of those functions that's less detailed
but still captures the essential structure
and still tells us something important about what they do.
In this video, I'm not making any changes or additions
to the design recipes.
You're still going to design functions that operate on lists the same way.
What this video does do is give you a new perspective on why
does functions work and how their templates sets them up to work.
And so what I want you to do is take this material now and maybe
watch it again once or twice in the next couple weeks.
And I think it'll really help you designing functions
that operate on all kinds of arbitrary size data,
to understand how those functions work and what their templates do for them.
So far this week, we've seen two list types-- list of string and list
of number.
Both of them have welf-formed self reference because of the self reference
in the type comments.
Both of them also have a natural recursion in the template functions.
In fact, these two types are very similar to each other.
They really only differ in the name of the type of value included,
strings in one case, number in the other case.
So for what I want to talk about now, we can just look at one of them.
We'll just look at list of number.
Again, we see that it has a self reference
in the type comment, which leads to a natural recursion in the template.
What I want to do now is look for a minute
and how the three functions we've designed so far
each fill the different holes in the template.
Here's what I mean by that.
If we look at some on the left and the [INAUDIBLE] for list of number template
on the right, then we look at what are called,
for now, the red hole in the template.
I'm going to give it a better name in a minute.
But for now, we'll just call it the red space in the template.
In the sum function, the red space gets filled with zero.
The green space gets filled with plus.
Nothing changes in the blue space.
We just leave it the way it was.
Count starts off quite similar to some.
It fills the red space with zero, the green space with plus,
but it changes what happens in the blue space.
Whereas in sum, we add the first of lon into the natural recursion.
In count, we just add one into the natural recursion.
Now, let's look at contains UBC.
In contains UBC, the red space is false.
And look what I've done here with the blue and the green.
For the blue, I've said that what happens in this function
is that it wraps string equals question mark to UBC around first of los,
and I'm calling that the blue.
And I've got green stuff both before and after the blue.
It's that if expression with its true answer and its false answer.
Why am I doing that?
Well, here's why.
Let me now talk about the name that I want
to give to each of these three spots in the template.
I'm going to call the red spot base because, really,
what's sitting in the red spot is the base case
result of this function-- what the function produces in the base case.
For some, the base case result is zero.
For count, the base case result is zero.
And for contains UBC, the base case result is false.
That's fairly straightforward.
The blue, I'm going to call the contribution of the first,
or the contribution of the first to the overall result. So in the case of some,
each first element of the list, or each element of the list when it's its turn
to be first, contributes itself to the overall result.
Because sum is sitting there, adding together all the numbers in the list.
Now, how does that contribution work?
Well, that's what combination means.
Combination refers to the way in which the final function combines
the contribution of the first with the result of the natural recursion.
So in the case of some, the combination is
to add the contribution of the first, which is itself,
to the result of the natural recursion.
Let's look at count for a second.
We already saw that the base case result of count is zero.
What's the contribution of first in the case of count?
Well, it's one.
When we count the number of elements in the list,
we don't care what each element is.
We just care that it exists.
So each element contributes one to the overall result.
And the combination is still plus.
Now that we understand better what the blue and green are,
the contribution of the first and the way in which that contribution is
combined with the natural recursion, now you
could see why I colored things the way I did in contains UBC.
The contribution of the first is just to say is this element,
is the first element of the list equal to UBC?
And the combination is to say, well, if the contribution of the first
is true, then produce true.
If the contribution of the first is false,
then produce the natural recursion.
Now, why am I talking about this now?
After all, you've just designed three list functions.
This may seem a bit too hard for right now.
The reason I'm doing this now is to give you a bit of a preview of something
we're going to do in a couple weeks.
In a couple weeks, you're going to see that because we've been working really
systematically with well-formed type comments, which produced templates
in a well-defined way.
So that a lot of our functions that operate on lists
and other arbitrary size data have a common form,
it's going to be possible for us to write functions like some, and count,
and contains UBC, really, in just one line of code.
You will write them by basically talking about how
to fill the spaces in this table.
Now, we're not ready to do that now.
And I'm not trying to say that you need to do that now.
You don't need to be able to design one of these functions
just by filling in the table.
The reason I'm showing you this now is so
that when you design these functions the way we've talked about this week,
you follow the whole recipe, and you write out the template in detail,
and then you fill it in based on the examples.
Maybe when you're done designing the functions,
think for a minute about how that function's row in this table
would look.
And I think that'll help you as we go on form a more general view of what
these functions are.
So then in a couple weeks when we get to what's called function abstraction,
you'll really be ready to see how it simplifies
the writing of these functions.