GREGOR KICZALES: What I want to do now is the same thing
we've done with all the other beginning student language constructs we've seen,
which is to go over in a little bit more detail
the rules for forming function definitions and function calls,
and also the rules for evaluating function calls.
Before I get to those rules, I just want to show you
something, which is where you could find all the rules for the BSL language.
If you go to the course web page and you scroll here to the Languages tab,
then this page has all the rules for the BSL language including
how to form all the kinds of expressions we've seen
and the rules for evaluating them and so on.
The rule for forming a function definition is simple.
We start with open paren define because it's a definition.
And then we have paren and the name of the function
followed by the names of the parameters.
In the example we have so far, we just have one parameter c.
But we'll define other functions later that have more than one parameter.
And then we close that paren-- so this first part
has open paren, the name of the function, the name of the parameters,
and we close that paren.
And then-- and we always put it on a new line--
we have an expression which forms the body of the function.
So here's the example we've seen so far.
Define, the name of the function is bulb, the parameter is c,
and here's the body of the function.
To form a function call expression, we put open paren,
the name of a defined function, and then we
put some number of expressions corresponding
to the number of parameters the function has.
So for our bulb function, which has a single parameter,
we put a single expression after the bulb name.
And those expressions are all called operands.
To show you how the rules for evaluation related to functions work,
you're going to first start by getting a somewhat simpler example.
What I've got here is a call to bulb, where it's argument,
instead of already being a value, is going to be
another call, a primitive call.
And I'm also going to set up by putting the rules for evaluating functions
and primitive calls here on the right.
So let's see.
We look at open paren bulb and that tells us
that we've got a function call.
So the rule for evaluating a function call
is to first reduce the operands to values.
So now let's go look at the first operand.
The first operand is open paren string append.
So that's a primitive call.
So we now look at the rules for evaluating a primitive call.
And the first rule is to reduce operands to values again.
Notice that the rule-- the first rule for function calls and primitive calls
is the same.
You reduce the operands to values.
Well, let's see.
The string re and the string d are both already values.
So now we can apply the string append primitive.
And the first full step in the evaluation
is that we now have bulb with an operand of the value red.
So now, going back to the function call roles,
we have now reduced the first operand to a value.
So we reduced all the operands to value.
And now we're going to replace the function
call by the body of the function-- so I've copied the body of the function
down here-- but in the body of the function
we're going to replace every occurrence of the parameter
c by the argument-- the corresponding argument-- to the function,
in this case, red.
And now what do we have?
Well, open paren circle, this is a call to a primitive.
So notice the function call is completely gone now.
Once we replaced the call with its body, we just
work on evaluating the replaced body.
This is a call to a primitive.
The first rule for a primitive is to reduce all the operands to values.
There's three operands in this case and they are all already values.
So now, the second step of a call to a primitive
is to just apply the primitive to the values.
And the value of that primitive call is a red circle.
And now all we've got is a value so evaluation stops.
Let me just point one thing out to you about the way
I've done this hand step by step evaluation.
By writing all of the different steps of the evaluation in the definitions
window this way, what I can do now is actually run this.
And since there's four steps to the evaluation,
I should see the same result four times.
Because when Racket starts here and runs to the end
it gets a red circle, when it starts here and runs to the end
it gets a red circle, and when it starts with a red circle and runs to the end
it gets a red circle.
So if you do your step by step evaluation exercises in the Definitions
window like this and then run it, you can kind of
check whether you've got the right step by step evaluation
because you should see the same value repeated each time.
Now you understand how to define functions
and you know the rules for evaluating function calls.
As I said at the beginning, functions are
going to be incredibly important to all of our Racket programs
so it's really important that you understand how they work.
So if it's ever unclear to you, just come back to this video
and also be sure to work the practice problems that
are associated with this video.
Just as an aside so you understand how powerful functions are,
one of the most important theoretical results in computer science
says that if you have a language that just has functions-- just functions,
no strings, no numbers, just functions-- you
could actually write any program that can be written in any language.
Now, you know that's a theoretical result that makes academics happy.
A language like that would be pretty cumbersome to program
in so you would never do it.
Back in practical terms now.
We want functions, we want strings, we want images, we want numbers,
we want all of that.
Even so, functions are pretty central to the whole game.