GREGOR KICZALES: So far we've done quite a lot.
We looked at primitive data and primitive operations on that data.
You learned the How to Design Functions recipe, and the
How to Design Data recipe.
And you also learned the How to Design Worlds recipe for designing world
programs, like animations and games.
Most recently, we looked at compound data
and learned how to use that in world programs.
But so far all of the data definitions we've worked with
have been what's called fixed-size.
And this week we're going to add to our repertoire,
working with arbitrary sized data.
And what do I mean by arbitrary sized data?
I mean, the kind of data we use when we want to represent
an unknown amount of information.
Information that we don't know upfront how much there will be.
So for example, if we want to represent all of someone's favorite hockey teams,
or all the students in a course, we just don't know how many of those
there will be upfront.
And that's what we need arbitrary sized data for.
So that's what we're going to work with this week.
We'll look at how to do the data definitions.
And we'll look at the effect that has on functions we design on that data.