GREGOR KICZALES: Now we're going to work through an example of designing a data
definition from scratch using the How to Design Data
recipe and the accompanying Data-Driven-Templates recipe.
It's going to be a simpler example than the traffic light example
you saw earlier in the week.
What we're going to do over the next couple of lessons
is build up our skills to designing more complicated data definitions like that.
What I've got is the CityName starter from the HtDD module web page,
and it says, imagine that I'm designing a program that, among other things,
has information about the names of cities in its problem domain.
Design a data definition to represent the name of a city.
So the key first thing that we do when we design a data definition
is to work out the form of the information we're trying to represent.
And it might even be good to just write down a couple examples.
Maybe I'll put a little comment box right here,
and I'll write some example.
So one example city name is Vancouver, and another example city name
is Boston for example.
And these are all information.
OK, now the question is how am I going to represent that.
What I'm going to do is go to the course website,
and I'm going to go to the Design Recipes page,
and this again provides me an index into all the design recipes.
And I'll go to the How To Design Data recipe.
And this web page, I won't go through in detail now.
I'm just going to work through it by example,
but you should review it on your own.
It tells me about the basic parts of every data definition,
and I'll pick this up later and set it down off
to the right when we're working in DrRacket.
And the key thing it helps me do is decide what kind of data definition
to use based on the form of the information that we need to represent.
Now remember, we're trying to represent city names, things
like Vancouver and Boston.
And the thing about that information is that it's atomic,
and what I mean by atomic is you can't take it apart
into pieces that are still meaningfully part of the same problem domain.
So yes, it's true, I can take the city name Boston apart into the letters
B-O-S-T-O-N, but those aren't meaningfully part of a city name
in a sense.
They're not like neighborhoods of the city or something like that.
So this information is atomic, and the way
we represent atomic information is with a type comment that looks like this.
We simply have a new type name, and we say
what underlying primitive atomic data it's going to be represented as.
So going back over here DrRacket, I'm going to say city name is string.
A good way to represent this information is using strings,
so for example if we do this, the data that represents the city name Vancouver
is going to be the string Vancouver, and the data that represents the city
and Boston is going to be the string Boston.
So here's my type comment, CityName is String,
and now I need to provide interpretations so I type Interp.
And for simple atomic data, the interpretation
is often fairly simple, especially for a case like this.
We're just going to say the name of a city.
Now the next part of the data definition is something
that we didn't see in the last example, and we'll
talk about why that is more in a couple videos.
But we want to provide some examples of how the data definition represents
information.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to say to define City Name one is,
well, one good example is Boston.
And define City Name two, and another good example is Vancouver.
Now I'll be honest with you, providing examples of really simple data
definitions like this doesn't do that much work,
but again, we're learning the recipe now so that'll help
us more with more complicated examples.
And fairly soon we'll have data definitions
where examples really are going to help us understand the data
definition better.
So there's the examples.
The next step of the recipe is to produce
the template for this data definition.
Now to produce the template, what I do I go back to the course website,
and I go to the Design Recipes page, and I get the Data Driven Templates rules.
So here's the Data Driven Templates recipe, and the way this works is it
says for a given type name the data-driven template looks like this.
So what I do is I say define fn-for-city-name.
And we're going to be quite particular about the name of the template.
Naming the template directly after the type name
is going to turn out to help us quite a bit later on in the course.
And I'll pick as a parameter name for this template cn,
and now I've got to do something about the body here.
And what I'm also going to do is I'm going
to write Template rules used like this.
And now looking back at the Data Driven Templates page, what I see
is the way to produce the body is to follow the rules in this table.
What I do is I go to the type comment.
I look at the first word after is, so that's string.
And then I start working in this table from there.
Now the string is what's called an atomic, non-distinct type.
The best way to understand what non-distinct means is
to wait for a couple more videos, and then we'll
see what distinct examples are.
But string is right here, so this is the row of the table that I'm going to use,
and I'm not inside of a cond.
You'll see what it means to be inside a cond again in a couple of videos.
But for the body, I'm just going to say dot dot dot x,
where x is the actual parameter name.
So the body of this template is just going to be dot dot dot cn.
And I'm also going to right here the template rule that I used,
and the rule that I used was the atomic non-distinct rule.
And I'm also going to write the part of the type comment
that matched that rule, which in this case is string.
And now I'm going to run this.
And there's nothing really to run, but the key thing
is I didn't get any errors.
If for example, if I had made a mistake like I left a parenthesis off there,
then I would get an error right now.
And I would fix this poorly-formed template right now,
so I'll fix this poorly-formed template right now.
And now I've got this running properly, and what
I'll do is I'll comment out the template because we're never actually going
to call this template function, we're just
going to copy it into later function designs.
And I'll get rid of this now, this scratch work,
because that's already really captured in the data definition.
So there you go.
I've completed a first data definition by following the How
To Design Data recipe using also the Data Driven Templates recipe.
In the next video, we'll design a function
that uses this data definition.