GREGOR KICZALES: In this video we're going to start a big function design
problem that's going to last through several videos,
and it will lead us eventually to designing five functions.
That's not at all unusual.
In some function design problems you design many more functions than that.
Imagine, for example, designing a function that consumes a location,
and drives a car from its current position to that location.
I think you can easily imagine that that would
involve many, many, many functions.
The one we're going to do now, though, starts with one function
and will end up designing five.
The basic problem is we have a bunch of pictures or images
that we want to be able to store and present in different ways.
This problem will do a simple version of the presentation,
and later on will set the stage for more elaborate version.
So there's two parts to this problem.
First we have to design a data definition to represent
an arbitrary number of images.
And then we'll design a function to arrange those images in a nice way.
The video will pause here while you go ahead and do part a:
design a data definition to represent an arbitrary number of images.
I strongly recommend that you take the time to do this yourself right now,
rather than just restart the video.
But of course nobody's watching, so you can just
restart the video if you want to.