GREGOR KICZALES: Going back to the table again and still
thinking about just what inherently has to be inside this program,
we see that at each clock tick, we need to produce an image based
on the cat's current x-coordinate that shows the actual cat farther
and farther across the image of some background scene.
In this case, the background scene is white.
So here's a function that does that.
The function consumes a cat and produces an image.
And we're using a primitive here that you
haven't seen before called place-image.
But the way place-image works is it takes an image,
and then it takes an x-coordinate, a y-coordinate, and a second image,
and it places the first image at the given x,
y-coordinate on the second image.
So what this function's doing here is it's
placing the image of the cat, which happens
to be the value of a constant called CAT-IMG at the appropriate x-coordinate
in the middle of the background image, which happens to be called MTS.