GREGOR KICZALES: In the last video, you saw
me use the HtDF design recipe to design a very simple function,
but I went through it very quickly.
Too quickly for you to absorb the different elements of the recipe.
What I'm going to go through in this video
is the same design much more slowly and talk more carefully
about what I'm doing in each step.
What I recommend you do is have your computer open, open up Dr. Racket
and follow along with the design recipe as I'm going through.
At each step, you could stop the video and catch up in your Dr. Racket.
And I'll also recommend that you open up a web browser to the HTDF design recipe
page from the course website, so that you can follow along with that as well.
Then you'll be able to see what I'm doing
and practice it as it's going through.
Just like before, I've taken the doublestarter.racket file
from the HTDF module web page.
I've opened it up.
And here's the problem.
We're supposed to design a function that consumes a number
and produces twice that number, and the function should be called double.
Again, it's a very, very simple function.
Remember we're using simple functions to learn the recipe,
and then the recipe will let us do harder functions.
And also, just like in the full speed version of the video,
I've taken a copy of How to Design Functions recipe, which
I got from the Design Recipes page.
And I am setting here on the right hand side, so we can refer to it as we go.
The first step of the recipe is write the signature.
The job of the signature is to tell me what type of data a function consumes
and what type of data it produces.
In this case, the function consumes a number and produces a number.
So I write the signature with two semi-colons, a space,
capitalized number-- type names are always capitalized--
and then I make a little arrow and again capitalize number,
because this function produces a number.
If the function consumes multiple arguments,
then I'd have multiple type names before the arrow.
In this case, it just consumes one argument.
And I read this signature as saying the function consumes a number
and produces a number.
Now I need to write the purpose.
The job of the purpose is to give me a succinct description
of what the function produces given what it consumes.
So in this case, a good purpose is to say that the function produces
two times the given number.
Now I know exactly what it's producing in terms of what it consumed.
The purpose needs to say more than the signature.
So purpose, for example, that just says consumes a number
and produces a number isn't telling me anymore than the signature.
And that wouldn't be a good purpose.
We also want the purpose to be short.
Sometimes it's hard to write it short, less than one line.
But it's good to do so, because it starts
to help you understand the function.
And the stub is like a piece of scaffolding
that we're going to put in place for a short period of time.
It's going to help us with some other parts of our work.
And then we'll end up commenting it out or later in the course,
we'll just actually delete it.
So it only lasts a short while, but it will do an important piece of work.
What the stub has to be is a function definition
that has the correct function name, in this case,
double, has the correct number of parameters, in this case, one.
I'll just call it n.
And it produces a dummy result of the correct type.
Since this function produces number, I'll make the stub produce zero,
because zero is certainly a number.
So now I'm going to write the examples in tests.
We call them examples and tests, because they're going to serve both roles.
What I mean by examples is that oftentimes, it's
easier to design a general function if we
start with some very specific examples of what it's going to do.
So in this case, for example I might write check-expect
that if I call double with an argument of three, then
what I expect to get back is six.
And I'll also write check expect that if I call double with an argument of 4.2,
I'll expect to get back 8.4.
The reason I'm calling double with these two arguments,
the reason I have two examples, is I've said here in the signature
that the function consumes number.
And by number I mean real numbers, integers, natural,
all kinds of numbers.
And so I'm going to put two examples here just
to really illustrate that I don't just mean integers.
The first example might lead you to think I just mean integers.
We're going to talk a lot in the course about reasons to have multiple examples
and how many examples are enough for a given function.
But here's two examples for this function.
Because I've wrapped them in check expect,
they're also going to be able to serve as test.
And we'll see shortly how they're going to help
us code the final body of the function.
But first what we're going to do is make sure
that the examples, that the check expects are well formed.
And here's where the stub is going to help us.
What I'm going to do now is I'm going to go ahead and run this program.
And when Dr. Racket has a program that has check-expects in it, what
it does is it runs the check-expects and it checks to see for each check-expect
it will call double with three, and it checks
to see whether the result is six.
And then it will call double with 4.2 and checks
to see where the result is 8.4.
And if the result isn't what it's supposed to be,
then Dr. Racket reports that the test failed.
Now in this case both tests failed.
And I'm very happy.
The reason I'm very happy is both tests actually ran.
Here's what the stub is doing for us.
It's letting us make sure that the tests actually run.
They're going to fail, because the stub always produces zero,
and that's not the right answer for these cases.
But we're going to know that they ran.
And you'll see later as programs start to get big
that making sure all your tests are well formed
before you get further along in the process is a good thing to do,
because the sooner you find a mistake the easier it is to fix.
So here we go.
Both of these tests ran, and they failed, and I'm really happy.
I want to take a minute here to make an important general point
about the recipe.
And that is that every step of the recipe
is intended to help with all the steps after it.
For example, the signature helps us write the purpose,
because the signature tells us that the function consumes a number
and produces a number.
Similarly, the signature helps us write the stub,
because the signature says the function consumes a single argument
so this function has one parameter.
It's a number that's why I called it n.
It also tells us that the function produces
a number, that's why I chose zero as the dummy value for the stub to produce.
The signature also helps us write the check expects.
It tells us that this function, when I sit there right check expects double,
and then I ask myself what to put it.
Well, the signature tells me, put a number.
And then when I try to write the expected value,
the signature says that it's a number, and the purpose
tells me exactly how that number relates to the argument in the example call.
The key thing is when you're trying to figure out
what to write at one step of the recipe, look at what you wrote
at the previous steps of the recipe.
That's how the recipe is helping you, is it's letting you slowly build up
the knowledge you need to design the final function.
The next step of the recipe is the template
or sometimes called the inventory.
Starting next week, we're going to get richer and richer templates.
But for this week, the template is going to be quite simple.
The template is a function with the right function
name and the right parameter.
And for this week, the body of the template is just going to be (...n.
the way we're going to read that is we're going to read that as saying,
hey, the outline of this function is that it's
going to do something-- that's what the dots mean-- is do something.
It's going to do something with the parameter n.
That's the role of the template is to give us the outline of the function.
What we're going to do here is label the template.
And now we'll make a copy of it.
Put the copy here or remove the label from the copy,
and I'll comment out the original template.
What you're going to do later in the course
is you're not actually going to keep a copy of the template.
What we've found for the first few weeks of the course
that it helps to keep a copy of the stub and template around.
And that's why that's what I'm doing here.
There is the template.
It's the outline of the final function definition.
Now I'm going to code the function body.
In this step, I'm going to use everything
I've written before to help me know how to finish the function body.
One thing that's useful to do sometimes is elaborate the examples.
So in this example, I know the double of 4.2 is 8.4,
but what I'm going to do now is make it more clear to me why that's true.
The reason that's true is that it's times 2 of 4.2.
And now all at once, I know exactly how to finish this function body.
It's just times 2 of n, whatever n is.
The last step is to run the tests.
So I run the test here, and I get both tests pass,
which makes me pretty happy.
We'll see examples later about what to do when the tests don't pass.
Now you've seen the HTDF design recipe used twice
to design the same simple function.
In the last video, I went through it quite quickly.
And in this video, I went through it in slow motion
where I talked in detail about each step.
At this point, you should be starting to understand
what to do at each step of the design recipe.
If you don't necessarily feel comfortable with it,
then I would suggest that you take a blank editor tab
and rework the process of designing the function from this video
on your own step by step.
But when you do it, do be sure to have the HTDF design recipe
page from the website open.
Use that as a reference whenever you're using the HTDF design recipe.
Our goal is not for you to memorize the recipe.
Our goal is for you to learn how to use it as a resource
in designing increasingly more complicated functions.