GREGOR KICZALES: What I've done now is to jump
to the v.3 version of the Cowabunga solution.
That has the next cow solution, which we just developed a few minutes ago.
And I've actually done a bit more than that.
I've started doing the design for the render-cow function.
Just to save time, I did the first part of the design already.
So I've got the signature, the purpose, the stub, and I did the examples.
And the examples for this function are actually relatively straightforward.
If I render a cow that's at position 99 and has a positive velocity--
In other words, it's facing towards the right edge of the screen--
then what this function needs to do is to place
an image of the right facing cow at exposition 99,
at y position center y onto the background MTS.
And I need two tests for this function, because sometimes it
places a cow facing right, and sometimes it places a cow facing left.
And so I've got a second task here where the cow
is going in a different direction.
And to be honest, this test would actually
be a little bit better if I changed the x-coordinate just
to be sure that I couldn't accidentally have put in by accident 99
into the actual solution.
So let's just make this be 33, and we'll make that be 33,
and now those are two pretty good examples.
They vary both the direction that the cow is facing, and the x-coordinate.
So I've already got the template.
Let's just start filling this in.
Let's see, both examples tell me that I'm going to place an image.
And sometimes it's one image, and sometimes it's another image.
Let me just put dots there for a second.
And I always place the image at the cow's x-coordinate.
And I always place the image at center y,
and I always the image on the background.
That's all of it, except for this part here where I have
to decide exactly which image to place.
Now, there's two choices here.
One choice is I could start to put an if expression here
that would choose which cow image to use.
But I'm going to do something slightly different.
And it's going to be something that we talk a lot about the course
as we go forward.
Which is, I'm going to say to myself, you know, this function
is actually doing two things.
This function is deciding which image to use,
and putting it in the proper place.
Two tasks.
And as a general rule, we don't want functions that do two tasks.
We want each function to do one task.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to wish for a helper.
I'm going to say, you know, it really would be great here
if there was a function called Choose image,
and I could call that function with a cow,
and it would give me back the right image to use.
If I had that, then I would be done.
And so I'm just going to wish for that to exist.
And I have to wish in a little bit more detail.
I'll wish in a little bit more detail by writing the wish list entry for it.
So I'll say cow to image produce-- now, what does it need to do?
Well, it needs to choose the right cow, produce R cow or L cow,
depending on direction cow is going.
And the reason I write this signature on purpose right now,
and I write it in detail right now, is that right now after I've just
finished wishing for this function, I know what I want it to do.
So I'm going to take the trouble to write down what I want it to do.
And then I'm going to say oh, but this doesn't exist yet,
I hope it will someday.
And I'll make a stub.
Choose image, consumes a cow-- and it's got to produce some image.
I could make it produce the blank image.
In this case, I'll just make the stub produce the right cow.
And now I run this to see if it's well formed.
And it is well formed.
And what we're going to see, paradoxically,
is that one of these two render-cow tests actually passed.
The first one actually passed, just because the Choose image stub always
produces the right facing cow.
So now I've basically done render-cow, if somebody goes and fulfills
this wish that I made for Choose image.
And that somebody is going to be me a little
bit later when I say to myself, hey, what work remains to be done?
Let me search for bang, bang, bang-- oh, I need this function, Choose image.
OK, great.
Let me do it.
Let's see, what does it do?
It consumes a cow, it produces an image.
It produces either the right cow or the left cow, depending on the direction
the cow is going.
So I'm going to speed this up a bit.
I've got two examples, one example for when the cow is moving left to right,
so it's facing towards the right.
Another example for when the cow is moving the other way,
so I need the left cow image.
I'm going to go and get the template from cow.
And now, let's see.
There's two cases, so I'll use an if.
And the question is whether the dx of the cow is greater than 0.
If it is, I use the right facing cow, otherwise I use the left facing cow.
And there's a bit of an issue here I have to deal with,
which is what to do if cow dx is actually 0.
And in that case, I'm just going to go ahead and decide
to use the left facing cow.
And when I run it, I get that all my tests pass,
and that includes the three tests for Choose image,
but it also includes the two tests for render-cow,
because Choose image is a helper for render-cow.
So now render-cow is working completely, because choose-image
is working completely.
Let me just recap what happened there.
We were in the middle of coding the function render-cow.
And we knew we had to place an image, and we
knew where it was going to place the image,
and we knew it had to decide what image it was going to place.
And that's when this idea about each function
should only do one task came up.
What I did was I decided, you know, deciding where to put the image,
and deciding what the image is, is two tasks.
I'm going to delegate one of the tasks to a new helper function,
Choose image in this case.
We're going to talk a lot more about this idea of helper functions
as we go along.
And In some cases, we're going to give you very clear cut
and dried rules for when to use helper functions.
This is not one of those cut and dried cases.
In this case, you have to kind of decide that Choose image is
its own separate task.
And some programmers wouldn't make a separate function for Choose image,
because it's so small.
But this is a reasonable place to use a helper function,
because it really is a separate task here.
And as we work through this part of the course,
we want you to look out for places where there is a separate task
and it makes sense to use a separate function.
What is clear that when I go back to read this function,
and I go to read render-cow, it says, OK, let's see.
I'm going to place an image, and somebody else
is going to choose the image, and I'm going
to put it at the cow's x-coordinate, center y and MTS.
That's very clear to me.
It says, I'm placing the image and somebody else is choosing the image.
And now when I go down here and read choose the image,
it says, well, if the dx is greater than 0, it's right facing.
Otherwise, it's left facing.
This code is easy to read.
And at this point, I have all of my handlers done except for handle-key.
So I actually can run this program at this point.
I could say, Main, make-cow, the cow that starts at the left edge
and is moving three pixels per tick, and there is our little cow.
I'll leave it to you to finish the key handler.
As I said, the solution is there in Cowabunga v.5.
And the problem description also talks about a fun little thing
you can do where if you take the cow image and take each image and rotate it
a couple degrees left and a couple degrees right,
and then you take a speed that's for example an odd number,
and you arrange to use different cow images depending
on whether the position is and odd or an even number,
you can make the cow appear to waddle as it crosses the screen,
and that looks kind of neat.
And there's all sorts of other fun stuff you can do here.
Just go ahead and have some fun with this cow program.
That will be good practice for doing this week's homework assignment.