GREGOR KICZALES: At the beginning of the week I showed you this picture.
And I talked about how the structure of this part of the course
was really going to be defined by the cross product of recipes like how
to design functions and how to design world programs with data
definitions with different structure.
During the week we saw the design simple atomic data definitions,
interval data definitions, enumerations, and itemization's.
And then we designed one function using each of those data definitions.
We basically completed the red box in this week.
Next week we'll do the green box.
That point that you can think about the organization of the first part
of the course in terms of a cross product between the form of the data
and how to design functions recipe, that points important.
But there's a much more important point that underlies that.
Think about the examples we've seen this week.
Think about the CityName example and the best? function.
The inherent structure of the domain information in that case was atomic.
So we represented it using simple atomic data.
And that meant the template had a certain form . . . x.
And that told us something about the function
and something about the test as well.
And that happened with all of the data definitions.
With SeatNum, the inherent structure of the information
is a continuous range of numbers.
So in that case we use an interval.
That formed the template a certain way.
It formed the body of the function a certain way.
And it told us something about the test.
In that case that there should be three of them.
Every example we saw this week there was the same phenomenon.
Which is that once we identify the structure of the information,
the inherent structure of the information, that gives us
the structure of the data used to represent it,
which gives us the structure of the template, which gives us
the structure of the function, and also we get guidance
about the test for that function.
So identifying the structure of the information
is really a key step in the program design.
At least for many kinds of programs, the ones
we're going to look at for the first two parts of this course.
As data definitions get more sophisticated, what you're going to see
is that there are different choices you can make about the data
that you'll use to represent information.
And by making different choices, you actually
have a lot of influence on the rest of the program.
Because of this fact that the structure of the data
determines the structure of the template,
determines the structure of the functions.
So designing data is a very high point of leverage for designing programs.
There are some programs for which that's less true.
But for a very many programs this approach
that we're taking in the first two parts of this course, this data driven
approach, does a very good job of producing the structure
of large parts of the program.
What we'll see later in the course is some examples where
the control structure becomes dominant.
And what we'll learn in that part of the course
is how to blend templates based with control structure
together with templates based on type comments,
or templates based on a form of data, to produce
the dominant structure of our program.
But even in those programs the form of the information
determines the form of the data.
And the form of the data determines the form of many of the functions
that operate on data.
So identifying the form of the information
remains a key step in the design of programs.
That's going to be true throughout the course and throughout all programs
you write.
So have fun with the homework assignments,
and I'll see you next week.