GREGOR KICZALES: Now let me just say a thing about templates.
Templates are not a beginner's approach to programming.
I told you in the intro video that the method
we're going to learn in this course is what I do when problems get hard.
And that's true.
So what templates are-- the way we mean them in this course--
is they're an expert's way of saying, gee, before I start on this function,
or before I start on this program, what do I
know about the basic structure of it before I get to the details?
So data-driven templates are saying, given that I know what type of data
this function consumes, what do I know about the structure of this function?
And the Big Bang World program template is
a way of saying given that I know I'm using
Big Bang, what do I know about the basic structure of this program
before I start?
And later on in the course, we'll see templates
where we know given that I know I'm using this basic kind of algorithm,
what must be true about the structure of the program
before I get to the details?
Templates are an idea that you can use throughout your career,
no matter how sophisticated a programmer you get to be.
When you get a hard problem and you don't quite know how to do it,
you first say, well, what do I know about the basic structure
of the program before I get to the details?
That's an incredibly powerful idea.
And it's not one that's just for beginners.
In the last video we started on the problem
of designing the world program the causes
the cat to march across the screen.
And we did the first half of the world program design recipe.
We did the domain analysis half.
That produced this domain analysis for us
in which we identify constant information, changing information,
and the required Big Bang options for this program.
In this video, we're going to start on the second part of the
how to design world's recipe, the build the actual program part.
And we're going to do steps 2.1, 2.2, and 2.3 three in this video.
So let's get the starter file.
And what I'm going to do now is I'm going
to go to the how to design world's recipe page.
And I'm going to scoot down here to the bottom.
And I'm going to take this template of a world program.
And I'm just going to copy this whole template right here
and bring it over into my program that I'm working on.
Now templates do something else important.
Or what I should really say is that the way the recipe is structured
does something else important, which is templates break the process of design
down into steps of the process, not just pieces of the solution.
So this function and that function are two pieces of the solution.
But what the template is is it's a step in the process,
because when you have the final function,
the template is kind of buried in the middle of it somewhere.
That's really important.
That's what happens when you design a method is you can design it
so that you both get pieces of the solution and steps of the process.
And so you get a kind of cross-cutting decomposition
that helps break the overall work down into smaller and more manageable
pieces.
So don't let anyone tell you the templates are just for beginners.
Nothing could be further from the truth.
What is true is that as you get to be a better programmer,
you won't template very simple functions,
or you'll kind of template them in your head or something.
But the idea of templates, the idea of getting
the basic structure of a piece of code before you get to the details,
you'll always have that idea.
And you'll always use it when the problem
gets too hard to just immediately write down the solution.
So here we go.
We need a better title than this-- a cat that walks
from left to right across the screen.
The first line of a program should give us a short summary of the program.
Now, we're going to do the constants.
And the constants are going to come directly
from the analysis phase of the program-- this analysis here.
So for example, one of the constants we identified
was that the width of the screen didn't change.
So here, I have to just guess a number.
I'm going to guess a number like 600.
In the rest of the program, we're never going to use the number 600.
We're always going to use the constant name WIDTH.
So if it turns out that this is the wrong number,
it'll be real easy to change.
We'll only have to change it in one place.
Here we go with the height.
And I'll say 400.
Another constant we identified is the y-coordinate of the cat.
The y-coordinate of the cat never changes.
So that's the CTR-Y. And here you might be tempted to put 200.
But what I'm going to do is follow the rule that every time I
need to refer to the height, I'm going to use the height constant.
So what I'm going to do here is put the HEIGHT over 2.
Now, if I change height, center y will also change.
And let's see, for the empty scene, the background of the scene,
there's a primitive called empty-scene.
And we'll make it WIDTH by HEIGHT.
And that would give us a sort of blank background.
If you wanted to make a background, if you
wanted to make a background that was a nice midnight blue or something,
you could, for example, instead make this overlay rectangle
WIDTH HEIGHT solid blue.
And that would give you a blue background.
I'll just stick with the simpler background for now.
And the last constant we identified was the cat image itself.
And for that we're just going to use this image here,
which the starter file gave us.
I'll go up there and copy it.
And then I'll come down here and paste it and there's the cat image.
And now would be good time to run.
In fact, I should have run after each of these definitions.
And I don't get any errors, so I know that my constants are well formed.
Now, let me reinforce the point I made before
about using the constants-- always referring to the constants.
Notice that this code that I have here lines up really well with the analysis
we did.
The fact that I can look at the analysis and look at the code
and understand where everything in the analysis showed up in the code
is a thing called traceability.
Both of those are important for the same reason.
And that is this is an important intuition.
The way to think about is there's only two kinds of programs in the world.
There's program that the change and programs that nobody uses.
Put it another way, any program that anybody uses is always changing.
People always want it to do more and better things.
And so what we're doing here is we're designing this program
to make it easy to change.
Using constant names makes it easy to change.
Having a clear traceability between the code and the analysis--
we'll see later-- that makes it easy to change.
OK, let's keep going.
Now I've got the constants.
The next step is to do a data definition that corresponds
to the changing state of the program.
The changing state of the program for my domain analysis
is the cat's x-coordinate.
So that's going to be-- that simple atomic data.
That's going to be something like a number.
The world program template has the beginning of a data definition here.
It has WS for world state.
But it says to give WS a better name.
And sure enough I will because WS isn't a very good name.
I'll just call it Cat.
And I'll say Cat is, let's say, Number.
And let's see, the interpretation is this
is the x position of the cat in screen coordinates.
And now I need some examples.
Let's see, one good example is 0.
And another example is-- well, let's see, the middle of the screen
is WIDTH over 2.
So that's kind of in the middle.
And that's kind of all on the right-- on the left edge.
And let's do this one.
And this is on the right edge.
So we'll run just to make sure everything is well formed.
And it is.
Now, we need a template.
Define fn-for-cat.
And this is just an atomic non-distinct case, so . . .
c.
We'll fill in the template rules used of atomic non-distinct and Number.
And it's also good to comment out the template.
And now we're good to go.
So there we go.
There's our data definition for Cat, for the changing world
state of the program.
Now we're going to proceed to our main function.
Now we decided not to use the name WS for the changing state of this program.
We decided to use the name Cat.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm going to say command F or Control F
on Windows.
And I'm going to take every occurrence of WS.
And I'm going to replace it with Cat.
Let's see we'll replace that one and that one.
And I won't do that one because it's a parameter name.
And I don't want to mess up the case.
I'll come back and do that one.
But I'll do all of these.
Oops, I didn't mean to do that one.
I'll come back and fix it.
I'm not going to do that one.
Now what's left is these ones that are parameter names.
And these I'll just change to c.
And there's that one there that I messed up.
And I'll just run now to make sure things are still well formed.
So now here what I've got from the template
is a main function that has lots of big bang options in it.
I'm not going to use all these options.
I'm only going to use on-tick and to-draw.
That's what my analysis told me.
So I'm just going to go ahead and delete all of this.
And I might decide that I don't like the name tock for the on-tick function
for this program.
So let's see, I could change the name tock.
Oops, I've got a parenthesis problem here.
I'm going to change tock.
I clicked on Check Syntax.
Now I'll click on tock.
I'll say Rename tock.
I'm going to call it advance-cat.
And I'll have to fix some of my spacing here.
Now what's going on here off to the right
is that the template for the word program in this main function
is reminding us of the signature of each of the handlers.
And the other thing the template for the world program did
is for these two handlers look at what we've got here.
For each of these two handlers we've got its signature,
its purpose-- but that's not filled in-- and a stub, which isn't filled in.
Let me just fill this in now.
It's produce the next cat by advancing it one pixel to right.
And that means that a good stub is just 0, because cat is number.
And this just says render the cat image at appropriate place on MTS.
These two things here-- the combination of signature, purpose, and stub
with those exclamation marks-- are what we call a wish list entry.
What we're doing here is we're saying, hey, up here when I wrote main,
I assumed that this function advance cat was going to exist.
And what I'm doing here is I'm writing a reminder
to myself of what it is I want that function advance cat to do.
I want it to have this signature, this purpose, and by the way,
there's a stub.
And this is a reminder of what I want the render function to do.
I want it to have this signature, this purpose, and by the way,
there's a stub.
Now, once my program is set up like this,
notice two interesting things about.
One is it turns out I can actually run it.
And I can even say main of 0 and run it.
Nothing happens of course, because my tick function doesn't do anything.
And my render function only returns the background see no matter what.
But it does run.
And the reason it runs is I have these stubs for the two big bang handlers.
I have a stub for advanced can.
And I have a stub for render.
The other thing I can do now is I can search for !!!
And I can see every place in my program that's incomplete.
By marking each of the wish list entries with some well known marker that says,
hey, this isn't done, I now know what I have to finish.
So now what I've done is I've got the overall structure of this program set
up.
I've got the constants.
I've got the data definition for the changing world state.
I've got a main function that calls big bang
with two options on-tick and to-draw.
And I've got wish list entries for advanced cat and render,
which are the Handler functions for those two big bang options.
And now, I know what I need to do in order to finish this program.
I have to design the advance cat function,
or I have to finish the design of the advanced cat function.
And I have to finish the design of the render function.
And then I should be done.
That's what we'll do in the next video.