GREGOR KICZALES: OK, that's the basics about strings.
What I'd like to do now is go look at some basics about images.
So what I'll do is I'll make a new Tab.
DrRacket has lots of different kinds of image functions.
In order to tell it we want to use the ones for this course,
we're going to type at the top of this file and any file
in this course that uses image functions: require 2htdp/image.
And what this is telling DrRacket is it means
we want to use the image functions that come from the second edition of the How
to Design Programs book.
So it's a little bit of a mouthful, but you can just
type that at the top of any file in which we're using image functions.
Now there's lots and lots of image primitives.
Some of them make images.
For example, the Circle primitive.
The first argument to circle is the radius in screen
coordinates, or pixels.
The second argument to Circle says whether the circle
should be solid or an outline.
The third argument is a color.
So that expression there produces that red circle.
So we call the primitive circle, we get a red circle.
And there's lots of similar shapes. rectangle-- rectangle
takes a width and a height.
And it can take outline or solid.
And we can try some of our other colors.
There we've got a rectangle.
And there's just a whole bunch of them.
I'm not going to go through all of them right now.
Another one that's quite useful, though, is called text.
Text takes a string, for example, Hello, and a font size, like 24.
And another color, like orange.
It produces-- this is now an image of the string
Hello in font size 24, color orange.
So this is an image, not a string.
So that's a bunch of useful primitives for making images.
Let me talk about some things we can do with the images once we have them made.
One useful primitive is above.
So if I say above-- we'll make a circle of size 10 that's solid and red.
And I'll make you another couple of circles.
What I'll do is I'll do this easily by cutting and pasting,
and then I'll just change the sizes.
Let's say we'll make this one 20, and we'll make this one 30.
And to make it pretty, we can change the colors, too.
There we go.
So now what happens when I run that is I get this stack of the images.
Above takes all the images that it receives as arguments,
and it stacks them one on top of the other.
So above is kind of a version of string-append for images.
But since images can be arrayed in lots of different ways,
there's lots of other functions.
So in addition to above, there is, for example, beside.
And if I run that, I get that shape.
In addition to Beside, there's a thing called overlay.
Overlay.
If I run that, overlay stacks them on top of each other.
There's lots and lots of primitives that operate on images,
and as you do the homework exercises this week,
you'll get a chance to look them up and play with them.
But for example, there's functions that make ellipses and stars
and triangles and things like that.
And you can line images up and put them next to each other in different ways.
But these are good set of basic functions right here:
circle, rectangle, text, overlay, above, and beside.
So I've got another little exercise you can do here
to test your understanding about primitives that operate on images.