GREGOR KICZALES: In this video I'm going to work
through a relatively straightforward How to Design Functions problem.
So this video would be a really good chance
for you to practice what you saw in the HtDF full speed and slow motion videos.
Just get the starter file and start working the problem
yourself and every now and then run the video
to kind of catch up to where you are in the problem
so that you can see that you're doing it kind of the way
that I'm doing it in the video myself.
OK, this first function is going to be simple, a lot like double.
We need to design a function called yell that consumes strings like hello
and produces strings like hello bang where the exclamation
mark has been added to the end.
So, let's see, the signature of this function is it consumes String
and it produces String.
What it's supposed to do is produce string
with bang added to end of supplied string.
And that's a little cumbersome, purpose statements
are often cumbersome the first time you write it, let's
see if we can do better than that.
What if we just say add bang to the end of s,
where s is the name of the parameter in the stub.
So that's simple, add bang to the end of s.
OK, let's write a check-expect.
Check-expect yell with hello that better produce hello bang like that.
And check-expect yell with bye had better produce bye bang like that.
Now, we run the tests, run the check-expects.
And both are failing.
But the key thing is both are running, so that
tells me that they're well-formed.
So I'll just ignore the fact they're failing for now,
I really just wanted to know if they were running.
And now what we'll do is we'll comment out this stub
and we'll label it as being the stub.
Let's see, the template for this function is define yell of s,
body of the template is . . .
s.
And what I'm going to do is select the template, make a copy of it,
paste the copy here, comment out the template
and label it as being the template.
Later in the course, you won't have to leave the template
behind but for now we find that it's helpful.
There's the template, and now I need to edit it.
Oh yeah, what this function does is it produces a new string
by adding bang to the end of s.
So that's just going to be string and s and bang like that.
Now we'll run it again, and both tests pass.
So there you go, that's design of the yell function following the HtDF
recipe.