GREGOR KICZALES: So now you've seen the How to Design Functions Recipe,
and you've seen me work through four examples of it,
where each example showed some more wrinkles to the process.
What you should do now is go work through all the practice
problems for this week, and then do the homework problems and the quiz.
Let me stress something about this material.
I just can't make this point strongly enough.
This is the kind of material that you learn by doing.
I really want to encourage you, don't look at the problem
and then look at the solution.
If you do that, you're going to say to yourself, oh, I know how to do this.
You need to actually take the blank starter file
and work through the problem yourself from beginning to end.
That's the only way to learn this kind of material.
At any rate, have fun with the practice problems and the homework,
and I'll see you next week.