GREGOR KICZALES: The problem in count-down-to-display-starter is
to design a function that consumes the countdown type we defined earlier,
and produces a little image of the current state of the countdown.
It might be something that would display on your phone
if you were watching the new year's eve countdown.
So again, the first step of the recipe is signature purpose stub.
We can do that quickly.
We're going to consume a countdown.
We're going to produce an image.
It's going to produce a nice image of current state of countdown.
The stub is what we want to call the function, countdown
to image of a countdown.
And the stub for functions that produce an image-- I
think it's kind of nice to make the stub just produce a blank image.
And the way I make a blank image is I make a square of size zero.
And it could be any color you want since it's a size zero.
But I make it like that.
That's our stub, let's run it.
Where this function is not defined this square right here.
Oh this is the bug about saying require 2htdp/image.
If we go to the top of the file, sure enough there's no require there.
So we'll say require 2htdp/image.
We'll run that.
OK, now we're OK.
So this is a good example of why we check the well formulas of stubs.
And in general, why we want to run our code as often as you can.
The sooner you find a little mistake, the easier it is to fix.
It's easier find one mistake now, and another mistake in a minute,
and another mistake in a minute, then it is to find all three of them
in three minutes.
So run your code as often as you can is the general rule we're going to use.
OK, so now we're going to do examples.
The question is how many examples do we need and what should they be?
So again, you can get some guidance for this by going to the how to design data
page.
Going down to the section on itemization, because this
is an itemization.
And the guidance here that says that there should be at least as many
tests as there are cases in the itemization.
And if they are intervals in the itemization
then there should be tests at all points of variance in the interval.
Let's go back to the code and I'll show you what that means.
Well, we know there are at least three tests.
So let's quickly do that. check expect countdown to image of some value.
Some value, I'll just make three of these.
We know there's at least three.
Let's see, the first one corresponds to this first case of the type comment
false, so that's false.
So now let's see, what should countdown to image
produce when the countdown isn't running?
Because remember, the interpretation tells
me this means the countdown has not yet started.
So if the countdown hasn't yet started, I don't know,
there's lots of things we could produce.
Let's just produce that blank image again.
You could produce something fancier than this.
The goal here is not to make the best possible version of this function,
but to understand what the design of this functions about.
So that'll be the first case.
And now we need a case for this interval.
Now, we're supposed to test every point of variance in the interval.
Conceivably we could test with one somewhere
in the middle like five and 10.
But in this particular function, the behavior
doesn't meaningfully vary across the interval.
Sure we're going to display one at one, and 10 at 10, and three at three,
but we're always going to display the number.
So it's going to really be enough to have a single test for this interval.
Maybe at five.
Now the question is what do we want to display?
Well let's see, we need an image.
And there's a function called text, which can turn a string into an image.
And there's a function called number->string that can turn a number
into its string.
So if we made a text of some size-- right now
I'm just going to put the size of the text here,
we'll see next week that the right thing to do is define a constant for this.
But I'm just going to put the size right there.
So what this is saying is it's saying if we countdown to image of five,
we should produce the text of the number five in font size 24 and it's black.
And what are we going to do if the countdown is complete?
Complete is the third case.
Well I say for that we'll just say text of happy new year.
And that'll also be 24, but maybe it'll be some brighter color like red.
Now a very important thing has happened here,
which is I've really worked out the behavior of this function
using the concrete examples.
So before I write in the actual code of the function,
we did a lot of the designing of the behavior of this function.
So that's the examples.
Let's run them.
Right, they all run, but some are failing.
That means they're well formed.
So now this was this stub.
Let's comment it out.
Let's put a note that says use template from countdown.
Let's get that template.
We'll copy it down here, and let's see, we rename it.
We rename it countdown to image.
So in the false case while this corresponds to this example,
so that's just that black image again.
In this case let's see, we're going to convert see whatever it is.
This will just be text of here's number to string of see size 24 and black.
And when conds get complicated like this we tend to put the question
and answer on separate lines.
That makes the cond easier to read.
And then this final case that corresponds to this example.
Which is just text.
Happy New Year 24 red.
Let's see what's happening here.
Let's try it.
number-to-string, this function is not yet defined.
I didn't get the error here though.
Oh, right, the doctor racket version of this function is named with an arrow,
like this.
One of the tests didn't pass.
Happy Near Year differs from Happy-- oh I didn't put the exclamation marks in.
Now let's try.
I'll save it and run it, and all three tests passed.
Notice I had to fix two bugs there.
In each case what I did was I read the warning message,
or I read the failing test.
I look at the highlighted code.
And I used that to give me an idea of what the problem was and how to fix it.
The key thing about having bugs in the code
is just to expect that that's part of it.
Don't get upset about it.
Don't worry about it.
It happens all the time.
It's just part of it.
The very best programmers in the world have bugs in their code.
Fixing it is part of designing good programs.
And we're going to talk more as we go through the course about techniques
for finding the bug as our programs get more and more sophisticated.
Now again, notice that the data definition
told us there were three cases.
It's an itemization that includes an interval.
That gave us the template.
It also gave us the examples.
And it helped us fill in the template for the function.
A lot starts with the data definition.
Let me show you one little side point here.
We saw that doctor racket names its number
to string function number arrow string.
And we named our countdown to image function countdown to image.
That's because this naming convention here
is something you're not going to get away
with in other programming languages.
So I wanted you to see this naming convention too.
But if you wanted to rename this function, let me show you a neat trick.
What you're going to do is you are going to click on check syntax here.
And now when I hover over countdown to image
here it shows me all the calls to it.
When I hover over one of these it shows me the definition that defines it.
Now what I'm going to do is on the Mac I'm going to Control click,
on Windows I'd right click.
And I go to Rename Countdown to Image.
And I'll rename it up here using other naming convention.
And notice how it fixed all of them.
But notice how I didn't fix the one that was in this comment.
It only fixes the ones that aren't commented out.
So now if you want to you've got the function named the other way.
This renaming command that I used is a thing called refactoring.
And it's very useful when programs start to get
big to have tools like that for doing things like re-namings.
We'll talk more about that as we go on in the course.