GREGOR KICZALES: For now I'm just going to kind of assume
that it only needs this one test.
That won't turn out to be right, but we'll see what happens.
Let me run the tests, and there's one test, and it runs and fails.
So it's well formed.
So we can keep going.
Let's see.
This is the stub.
We'll comment it out.
We'll write the template.
The template is tall, question mark img, . . .
img.
We'll make a copy of that and we'll comment out.
The original template, we'll label it as the template.
Let's see.
These functions have two cases, right?
Sometimes it's tall and sometimes it's not tall.
So when you have two cases, you can use an if, because that'd be the case where
it is tall, and the case where it isn't.
And what I'd like to do whatever I add an if to my template,
is I put in the if.
And then I make myself three copies of the rest
of the template as a way of saying OK, now I've got the if in there,
and I need to decide what happens here.
Now let's see: tall?
involves comparing the width to the height.
So let's see.
If the image height of the image is greater than the image
width of the image-- well, let's see.
If that's true, then the image is tall and so I should produce true.
And otherwise I should produce false.
Well, let's try running that.
OK, the test passed.
The test passed, but are we done?
Have we really tested this function?
Well, one clue that we haven't DrRacket is giving us right here
in the way it's colored this false.
Depending on how you have your DrRacket configured,
it might actually just highlight this false with black.
But in both cases, what it's saying is, it's saying hey,
this expression here was never evaluated.
There's this concept called code coverage for a test,
or test coverage, which says given all my tests, how much of the code
is actually being evaluated?
And if the answer is not all of the code,
then you don't have enough tests, because what
if the piece of code that isn't evaluated is wrong?
You haven't tested that piece of code.
So, whenever you run your tests, if you see
code that's highlighted that says that it didn't get evaluated,
then you know for sure you need more tests.
And what's happening for us in this case is we tested the case where it is tall,
but we didn't test the case where isn't tall.
In this case, we can do that fairly straightforwardly by copying
the first test and just swapping these two around.
And saying, well in that case, it's false.
Now let's run it.
Both tests pass, but are we really done?
Let me make this a little bit-- give us a bit more room here.
Are we really done?
At this point, what you might think of is, hey, wait a minute.
There's one more case.
What if it's the image width and the height are the same?
What should happen then?
And this is a thing that happens in function and program design
all the time.
You realize partway through the design process
that there's a boundary condition, or sometimes we call it a corner case,
that you hadn't quite thought of.
It's perfectly fine for that to happen, but when it happens,
when you say to yourself, "Wait a minute, what if the width and height
are the same?"
You need to immediately do a couple things.
First, write an example for it.
Then decide what the behavior is.
And I'm going to decide in this case that if your width and height are
the same, you're not tall.
So write the example, write the expected result, fix the purpose.
Height is greater than width, so that it's unambiguous in the purpose.
And if what you decided required you to change the function,
change the function.
In this case, it didn't, but if I had decided this the other way,
I would have to change that to a greater than or equal.
And now I'll run the tests again.
Now all three tests are passing.
So that's the design of that function.
That works when I run it, and the tests pass.
All my code is evaluated, so I've got good test coverage.
So I'm pretty good here.
At this point, I just want to make one minor detail
point, which is whenever you have an expression of the form if something,
true, false, you can always replace that by just this simpler thing.
Let me comment this one out bracket, comment, out, with semicolons.
Why are these two the same?
Well, look.
This one says if this expression evaluates to true, then produce true.
Otherwise, if this expression evaluates to false, then produce false.
So that's really just the same as the expression itself.
Either this expression evaluates to true or it evaluates to false.
So whenever you have if, something, true, false,
you could just replace it with the question itself.
And in a normal program, once you've done something like that,
you would clean this up.
You'd delete that out from there, and in a couple weeks,
you also won't leave the stub and template behind.