GREGOR KICZALES: In the last video, we looked
at how to represent information about an arbitrary
number of accounts using a list, where each account has a number and account
name.
At the end of that video, I asked you write a function that would look up
an account number in such a list and produce either the account name,
if it could find it, or produce false, if it couldn't.
So I hope you've done that, and I hope that gave you
some better understanding of what that representation of accounts
would be like.
Now, let me ask you a question.
Suppose we had a list like that, of accounts.
And suppose the list is long, really long.
And I don't mean 365 along.
Maybe I mean 365,000 long, or I'll just call it n, for now.
The question I want to ask you is, how long does it
take to find an account in that list?
Well, let's see, if I get lucky, and I'm looking for account number one,
then I only have to look at the first account in the list to find it.
So that was pretty lucky.
If I get a little less lucky, and I'm looking for account number four,
then I only have to look at the first two accounts in the list to find it.
If I get less lucky and I'm looking at, say, account number 14,
I've got to look at five accounts.
If I really get unlucky, and I'm looking at account 365,
I have to look at all n accounts in the list before I get to 365,
because I have to check each of the ones that come before it,
to see that, oh no, they're not account 365.
So on average, if I have average luck, I'm
going to have to look at n over 2 of the accounts,
because sometimes I'll be lucky, and I'll be looking for the first one.
And sometimes I'll be unlucky, and I'll be looking for the last one.
And everything else in the middle will happen.
And so on average, I'm going to look at n over 2 of the accounts.
So that's not so good.
If I have 365,000 accounts, then any time I look up an account number,
I'm going to have to look at half of 365,000.
That's not really good enough.
It seems like we ought to be able to do better.
Well, one idea would be to sort the list by account number,
so that account number one comes first, then three, and four, and seven.
And so it's just in increasing order of account number.
That would take some work to get it sorted,
but it seems like that might be a good idea.
The problem is that doesn't help me.
It doesn't help at all, not at all.
And here's why.
The way lists work, remember that with lists, we just have first and rest.
So the only way we can traverse the list is in order, from beginning to end.
So whether the list is sorted or not, on average, we're
going to have to look at half the accounts in order to find the one
we want.
So sorting is not going to help.
Or actually, what I should say is, sorting alone isn't going to help.
Here's another idea.
Let's imagine that we start with a sorted list.
And then, we'll take the middle of the list, in this case, that's 10y.
We'll take the middle of the list, and we'll split the list around the middle,
so that we leave the middle up top, like this.
On the left-hand side, we're going to put
everything that came before the middle.
And on the right-hand side, we're going to put
everything that came after the middle.
And so the important thing, here, is that in this left-hand list,
this one down below on the left, all those
have an account number less than the middle, less than 10.
In the right-hand lower list, all of those
have an account number bigger than 10.
So that's kind of neat.
We can do it again.
For each of those lists, we can take the middle.
So in the left-hand case, it's 3 I-L-K, and in the right-hand case,
it's 42 I-L-Y. And we'll do the same thing.
And we could keep doing that, until we get to the point
where there's no lists left, where at each level,
all we have is a single account number and name.
And now, I'm going to draw these lines in.
And this is a thing called a binary search tree.
And the important thing about a binary search tree
is that every single what's sometimes called
a node, all the accounts in the left subtree of that node
have a number less than the root, and all the accounts in the right subtree
have a number greater than the root.
So everything in this part, over here, has an account number less than 10.
Similarly everything in this part, here, below and to the right of 3 I-L-K,
has an account number greater than three.
And this rule, here, is called an invariant,
and it holds true over the entire tree.
That's what it means for it to be an invariant.
It's true over the entire tree.
Now, if I construct a tree like this-- we don't quite yet
know how we're going to represent it.
This is all information.
But imagining that this is information, let's
think abstractly about how long it would take to find something in such a tree.
Well, let's see.
Suppose I'm looking-- suppose it's going to be the worst possible case.
I'm going to look for 14, for example.
Well, I look at 10.
And 10 isn't 14, so I'm not there.
But 14 is greater than 10, so I'm going to completely ignore
the left-hand part of the tree.
And now, I'm going to go down to the right branch of the tree.
Let's see.
42 isn't 14, so I'm not there.
But 14 is less than 42.
So at this point, I'm going to ignore the entire right-hand branch
of the tree.
And I'll go down the left-hand branch.
Let's see.
27 isn't 14, so I'm not there.
But 14 is less than 27, so I'll ignore the right-hand branch of the tree.
There happens not to be one, so ignoring it doesn't do much, but I'll ignore it.
And I go down the left branch.
Let's see.
14 is 14.
I'm there.
I produce LLP.
And if I ever get to a branch which has nothing in it--
suppose I've been looking for 28, for example.
If I've been looking for 28, then when I got here, to 27,
I would have tried to go to go down the right-hand branch.
And there's nothing there, and so I would produce false.
So how long does it take to find something in that tree?
Well, notice that at each step of the process, when
we didn't find what we were looking for, we eliminated about half the tree.
So each time, the tree gets smaller by half, as compared to the list.
Each time, the list got smaller by one, but here, each time, the tree
gets smaller by half.
And so what that means is that in this world,
on average, we're going to have to look at log n of the size of the tree,
because the tree keeps getting smaller by half each time.
And so we're going to find our answer a lot faster in something like this,
if, of course, we can find a way to represent it as data.
Right now, we're talking about an abstract piece of information.
And we've done an abstract analysis of how long it
would take to find something in it.
We'll try to implement it in the next video.