GREGOR KICZALES: This week we're going to talk about the design of data.
And what we're going to see is that the design of data
really turns out to be a point of leverage in designing programs.
Because when we design data, we make decisions about all the functions
that later operate on that data.
But before we get to that, this video covers cond expressions.
Which are a new kind of expression in racket
that's going to let us program conditional behavior where
there's more than just two cases.
I have the cond-starter.rkt file opened from the lecture page.
Let's just look at this file quickly.
It starts by defining three constants, called I1, I2, and I3.
And they're all three rectangles.
And let's see, I1 is 10 wide and 20 high, and I2 is 20 by 20,
and I3 is 20 by 10.
So these are three rectangles of different shapes.
Now here's a function design.
And the function consumes an image and produces a string.
And let's see, it produces the shape of the image,
one of tall, square, or wide.
And these three examples slash check expects really
help me understand this function.
If I ask for the aspect ratio I1 I get tall.
Whereas for I2 I get square.
And for I3 I get wide.
And reading through the rest of this there's
a stub and a template that are commented out.
Now when we look at the definition of the function, what does it say?
It says well if the height of the image is greater than the width of the image
then produce tall.
That's this whole if there.
And that's its question.
And that's it's true answer.
On the other hand let's see it's false answer is another
if that asks if the image height and width are equal produce square
otherwise produce y.
So this function design works and if I run it, I'll get what I want.
But there is something I'm not entirely happy about here.
If you think about this function there are really three cases, right?
There's the tall case, the square case, and the wide case.
And those three cases really feel like they're parallel to me.
They feel like they're corresponding cases.
Whereas when we implemented here with if, we end up having one case tall.
Which has two other cases square and wide kind of inside of it.
And that doesn't feel quite right.
It doesn't feel quite right to have one case with two inside of it,
as opposed to three parallel cases.
So what we're going to learn in this video is a new mechanism called cond.
That's what's called a multi armed conditional.
And that is something we can use when we want
to make an expression that has different behavior depending
on the answer to predicates.
But there's more than two different options.
So here we go, let's do it to this one.
Let me first show you a new trick.
If I do sharp sign semicolon, that's going to comment out
the entire-- all of that stuff.
It basically comments out from balanced parentheses to balanced parentheses.
It's easier than putting a semicolon before each line.
Now let's redo this function.
I'll say define aspect-ratio image.
And what I have is three cases.
So what I would do is I'm going to write cond, and then there's three cases.
And each case has a question and a answer.
And there's three of them.
So I'll just copy that like that.
Oh, and I spell the name of it wrong.
Now notice something here which is that I'm
using square brackets instead of round parentheses
around the question and answer pair.
That's just a convention to make the question and answer pairs stand out
better.
Particularly when they get larger.
Square brackets and round parentheses are really treated the same by racket.
Square brackets balance each other and round parentheses balance each other.
You could use round parentheses here, but square brackets just
makes it look a little bit better.
Now what's the question for the first case?
Well the question for the first case is actually right here.
I'll take that, and I'll replace that question with it.
And if that question is true, then what's the answer?
Well the answer is right here.
And what's the question for the second case?
Well the question for the second case is right here.
And the answer for the second case is right there.
And then what's the question for the third case?
Well, the third case is the last case.
It's the in all other cases case.
And so there's a special question that we could put there called else.
Which means if it wasn't the first one or the second one, just do this.
And the answer for the last case is wide.
Let me first run this to make sure I haven't made any mistakes.
I haven't and it's working.
And so the way I want read this is it says, gee, there's multiple conditions.
If image-height is greater than image-width.
then produce this result. Evaluate this expression and produce that result.
If image-height is equal to image-width, evaluate this expression
and produce that result. Otherwise or else, evaluate that expression
and produce that result.
And that's kind of nice.
What that gets me is multiple questions.
Kind of all at the same level of nesting.
All at the same level of important in some sense.
So cond is a good thing to use for multiple case expressions
when there's more than two cases.
You can use if.
You can use if and nest them the way we have up here.
But, it tends to read more easily if you use cond
when there's more than two cases.
Now we'll do the usual thing and look at the rules
for forming a cond expression.
It's just open paren cond.
And then one more question and answer pairs.
Where each question answer pair is open bracket,
a question expression, and then an answer expression, and a close bracket.
And all the question expressions have to produce a Boolean,
except the last question expression, which
is allowed to be the special word else.
Which is going to mean if you get to this question answer pair,
definitely produce this answer.