GREGOR KICZALES: So in the last two videos,
we saw some pretty amazing stuff.
We had a type comment that referred to itself,
and then we had a function that called itself.
And that function actually did what we wanted it to do,
instead of just going to around and around in circles,
on and on, and on forever.
Now why is that?
That's what I'm going to talk about in this video.
There's some pretty deep computer science underlying all of this,
and we're not going to get into it and kind of academic terms.
But what we will see is that the type comment has two key properties.
And the way we derive the template preserves those properties,
so that we end up with functions that work properly,
even though they call themselves.
So what I'm going to do is explain that, make a few additions
to the design recipes, so you can keep doing that
systematically, and producing recursive functions that work properly
on your own.
This file is Quidditch recap starter.
It's basically just the solutions from the last two videos,
rearranged slightly so that I have both parts of the problem in one box.
That gives me some more room below.
The first thing I want to know is right here in the problem description.
Notice that we're designing a program that will keep
track of your favorite Quidditch teams.
Now ask yourself, how many teams are there?
We don't know ahead of time.
There could be one, there could be two, there could be 30, there could be 60,
we just don't know ahead of time.
This is what we call arbitrary sized.
Arbitrary doesn't mean random, it just means we don't know ahead of time.
Now, whenever we have an arbitrary sized data
problem, whenever we need data to be of arbitrary size,
what we're going to see that we want to use self reference in the type comment.
This type comment has the self reference in it, as we noted before,
and we saw how that made it possible for it to account for lists of any size.
We just make one more cycle around the self reference relationship
for each element of the list.
But why does this self reference work out?
Why doesn't it in some sense blow up, because it just keeps going round?
Well the key thing is this is what's called a well formed self
referential data definition.
And it's well formed, because it has the self reference case, that's true.
That's what lets it get longer and longer.
But it also has the non-self referential case, or the base case,
and that's what lets it stop.
So in a well formed self referential data definition,
you always have both the base case, that has no self reference,
and a self reference case.
Now this is a simple self referential data definition.
It's possible for these type comments to have more than one self reference
case and more than one base case.
The rule for being well formed is that there
has to be at least one base case, non-self referential case, and at least
one self referential case.
So the summary so far is, if you have an arbitrary amount of information you
need to represent, you need to use a well formed self referential data
definition.
That gets us to here.
And if we look at how to design data page, what we've got so far
is reflected here in the choice of what form of data definition to use.
When the information to be represented is of arbitrary size,
we use a self referential data definition.
Mutually referential is something we'll talk about another week.
So if we follow this link, it says that for arbitrary size information,
we need to use a well formed self referential data definition.
So that's the how to design data recipe accounts
for what we've seen the code so far.
Let's go back to the code now, and let's talk quickly about the examples.
For soft referential data definitions, it's
good to have examples of the base case.
If there's more than one base case that have examples of both base cases,
they tend to be kind of trivial, but I like to put them in anyways.
And you should have examples of the self referential case,
in this particular data definition I probably
could have done with just two examples, rather than three.
So I probably could have done with example one and example three.
It's fine to have an additional one.
Now, let me scroll a bit and talk about the template.
As we saw before, the beginning of the template's relatively straightforward.
It's one of the two cases, so that got us to cond.
The first cases is atomic distinct empty,
so that got us cond empty question mark, LOS, and dot, dot, dot.
This case, the second case, is com, so that's compound.
We take the coms apart into its first and it's rest.
But then the question is, how did we get this fun for LOS.
Well, the reason we got that from for LOS, let me
just back up a little bit to where we were right at that point in time.
We knew the first LOS was going to be a string,
and we knew that rest LOS was list of string.
So we're not going to do anything with first LOS,
because it's primitive type, string is a primitive type.
But with rest LOS, here's where we're getting the self reference.
There's a self reference here back to listed strength.
When we take the rest of LOS, we're holding a value of type list of string.
And so there's a special template rule, called the self reference rule,
and we use it in this case.
And the self preference rule says wrap that
selector in a call to the template function itself.
And this thing is what's called a natural recursion.
It's of recursion that shows up exactly where in the type comment,
we have a self reference.
So what we have so far is arbitrary size data, well formed self referential data
definition, have examples of the base case, and the self reference case.
And in the template, when you hit the self reference,
put in a natural recursion.
That last bit shows up in the data driven templates page right here,
where it says, if you have a self reference
to form a natural recursion with a call to this type's template function.
And that's what we did here, we put a call to this type's template function,
because we had a self reference there.
And that's why this call, this natural recursion,
corresponds exactly to this self reference.
And I tried to draw the arrows here, to show that correspondence clearly.
So from now on, whenever you see a self reference in a type comment,
you'll immediately know there's going to be a natural recursion in the template.
Now let's look at the function we design.
So the signature is pretty straightforward, nothing really new
here except that it does consume list of string.
The purpose, similarly, we knew how to do, and the stub.
And the check expects look pretty familiar,
but there are a couple things I want to note here
about check expects for functions operating on lists.
First, remember that check expects are always examples first, and tests later.
So we use them as examples to help us figure out what we're doing.
And with that in mind, it's always a good idea
to have the base case example first, the base case test first.
That's what I have here, I have contained UBC of empty
as my first test.
Partly, that helps us figure out the simplest case first, and also
many tests of these functions end up at the base case.
And so if the base case result is wrong, that can affect other tests.
So it's good to get the base case debugged first.
So there's two reasons to put the base case first.
One, it helps us figure out the simplest thing first.
And the other, it makes sure, when we run the test,
that the base case works properly before we test the other cases.
And another general guideline for functions operating on list
is to be sure that you have a test that operates on a list that's
at least two elements long.
That's because sometimes there's certain kinds
of bugs you can introduce that don't show up in one element list.
This particular example is also an example
of a function that has two different cases in it.
There's cases where it finds the string it's looking for and cases where it
doesn't.
And so, in that case, of course, you have
to be able to test the true and false case.
Finally, let's look at the function itself.
And to look at the function, what I want to do is I'm going to back up.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to delete this and go back to the point
where we just have the template.
When you copy the template down, for a template based
on a type with self reference, then the template has a natural recursion in it.
And it's very important when you rename the function, that you
rename both the function definition, and any natural recursion.
That's very important, and we'll see why in a minute.
So now, let me start coding the details .
Let's see if the function is operating on a list that's empty.
Then we can't find UBC in empty list, so that would be false.
Otherwise these examples tell me that there's two different cases,
depending on the first item in the list.
If the first item is UBC, we produce true.
If it's not, we need to go look farther down in the list.
So that makes me put an if in here, and I say, string equal question mark UBC.
If the first in the list is UBC, we're going to produce true.
And otherwise, what do we need to do?
Well, the first item in the list might not be UBC,
but there might be a UBC farther down the list,
so we need to go look further down in the list.
And the key point here is that we want to get
you to trust the natural recursion.
At this point in time, you need to know is UBC in the rest of the list?
And because the template has included a natural recursion,
and because that natural recursion came from a type
with well formed self reference, you could count on the natural recursion
to work.
So we're just going to trust that contains UBC of rest LOS
does what we need it to do.
The key thing is I want you to avoid the temptation to edit in here.
Trust the natural recursion, that's the game.
And the reason you could trust it is again,
is because it came from a well formed self referential type.
Let's see, all four test passed.
What I'd like you to do now is go look at the how to design functions,
and how to design data, and data driven templates web pages,
and pay attention to the parts that talk specifically
about designing with lists.
Just go ahead and review that.
And then, you'll be in a good position to keep
designing with lists going forward.
And remember, the big summary of kind of what we've seen so far
is, if you have arbitrary size information,
then you need arbitrary size data.
That requires a well formed self referential type comment.
That leads to a natural workers in the template.
That leads a recursive call in the function.
You should test the base case first, and you should always
trust the natural recursion.