GREGOR KICZALES: This video is called a parlor trick
and it's intended to mess with your mind a little bit.
What I want to do is show you the power of representing information as data
and get you to explore some of the data representation choices
we maybe take for granted.
It's going to be a little weird.
You may need to watch it a few times to really enjoy it.
So the problem set up is, I don't know, maybe a little crazy.
You've just gotten a new tablet and it runs a prototype version
of Racquet, which is great.
You can make your tablet do anything you want.
But there's one problem, which is this prototype version of Racquet doesn't
include numbers as primitive data.
There just are no numbers in it at all.
Fortunately, it does have cons and first and rest and strings.
And you know what the self referential data definition is for numbers
and you know that it's based on the idea that add one is kind of like cons
and sub one is kind of like rest.
So you actually know how to solve this problem
and define your very own numbers from scratch.
Here we go.
We'll make a new type called NATURAL.
I'm making it all uppercase to distinguish it
from the old time called natural.
And we'll just say, like the old type, that it's
going to be a well formed, self referential data definition.
And it's going to look like this.
We're going to say that it could be either empty
or it could be cons, an exclamation mark, a string with an exclamation
mark on a NATURAL.
So you've got a well formed, self referential data definition there.
Empty is clearly the base case and cons "!"
NATURAL is the self reference case.
So that's the type con.
But in this case, what's actually trickier
than the type comment is the interpretation.
What does that mean?
Well, it just means this.
It's a natural number.
And the number exclamation marks in the list is the number.
Let's do some examples.
So natural zero is empty and natural one is cons one exclamation mark
onto natural zero.
This is one and this is zero.
And two is just cons another exclamation mark onto N1.
That's two.
Let's just run this for just a second and take a quick look if we
go down here in the interaction window.
N0 is empty.
N1 is a list with one exclamation mark in it
and N2 is a list with two exclamation marks in it.
So they're cumbersome to look at.
They'd be even more cumbersome to type.
But those are new natural numbers.
They would be so cumbersome to write out, in fact, that what I'm going to do
is I'm going to use the magic of video editing
to very quickly get a whole bunch more of them.
Now we've got natural numbers zero through nine
that are relatively easy to type.
It's still a little weird looking at that cons.
What's really going on here is that these are the primitives that
operate on the new kind of natural.
One is the predicate zero.
It's something zero.
And something is zero if, what?
Well, if it's empty.
Because that's what the type comment says.
The type comment says-- the type comment plus the interpretation
says that the way we represent zero is with empty.
So that's one primitive.
Another primitive is at one.
And the way we're going to add one to a natural
is, well, we just do this cons thing.
And another primitive is sub one.
And the way we're going to get the next smallest natural number is with rest.
Even though these are primitives, let me just write the signatures for them
off to the side so we'll have them.
We've never defined primitives like this before.
Let's see-- zero question mark actually consumes anything.
And it produces a Boolean to tell us whether what it consumed
was the representation of zero.
Add one consumers one of these newfangled
naturals and produces one of these newfangled naturals.
And sub one consumes one of these new kinds of naturals,
but it has to be bigger than zero.
That's a restriction that's kind of like the restriction and rest has, right?
Rest won't take empty.
Rest needs a cons.
Rest need to list that's at least one long.
So if you give sub one a natural that's at least one or bigger,
you'll get back another natural.
And if you want, we can pretty this up a little bit.
So there's our permanence.
Now let's do the template.
We'll do it like this-- fn-for-NATURAL n.
Let's see-- it's a one of.
I won't write out the template rules used.
I'll just save them as I go.
That's where we're going to be doing starting next week.
So I'll do it in this last video of this week.
Com-- it's a one of.
There's two cases.
The first case is atomic distinct.
Now, remember-- that empty really means zero.
And the reason I wrote these primitive so
that we wouldn't go crazy when we saw ourself calling
empty on something that looked like it was supposed to be a natural.
So I'm going to say zero here.
If the natural is zero, that's atomic distinct.
Otherwise, dot dot dot.
And we'll put in n because we know it's useful.
And we'll say fn-for-NATURAL sub one of n.
And of course, now that I have these primitives,
this template looks just like the template for ordinary natural numbers.
Because I've got my own special version of zero
and my own special version of sub 1.
So remember, we're doing kind of a weird thing here.
We're recreating the numbers.
We're recreating the numerals, in some sense, OK?
We're recreating the representation of the natural numbers.
So there's the template.
Now let's do some functions.
Well, we've got zero, add one, and sub one.
One thing we don't have is plain old add.
We don't have a way of adding together two naturals.
Let's do that.
Well, it's a function that consumes two natural and it produces a natural.
And its purpose is to produce a plus b, assuming that's the name of the two
are naturals.
I'll give the stub here.
We'll call it add.
So let's do some examples.
Now, this function is clearly going to be recursive on one of the numbers.
That's what the template is for.
I'm going to make it be recursive on the second number.
It turns out that works out a little bit better later.
It would have worked perfectly fine to make it recursive on the first number.
But it'll just simplify things later if I do it this way.
So that means my first test should be with a base
case for the second argument.
So I'll say N2 and N0.
Zero is the base case.
If I add two and zero, I should get two.
And just to make sure the first argument is treated all right,
I'll also do something like this.
That should be three.
Because if I add two and zero, I get two.
If I add zero and three, I get three.
And now let's make one that actually does some more work.
We'll add N3 and N4.
This satisfies my at least two long rule because four is bigger than two.
And we'll get N7.
Sure is good that I made those constants so that I don't have
to take these natural out all the time.
Doing this with a bunch of conses would be a pain.
OK, let's take the template.
We'll bring it down here.
We'll rename it.
We'll rename the recursion.
We'll comment out the stub.
And we need two parameters.
So I'm going to rename this parameter to B and I'll add a parameter A.
And in the recursion, I'll add the parameter A also.
So let's see.
If I'm adding two numbers, A and B, and B is zero, this is the base case.
What's the result?
Well, I know from arithmetic and I also know from this example
that the result should be A, if you add A to zero,
you get A no matter what A is.
What do I do in this case here?
Well, I don't know if you remember the way you were originally
taught to add in kindergarten, but the basic idea
was you would get maybe two piles of sticks.
And you would add them together by moving
one stick at a time from one pile to the other pile until you only had one pile.
And if you counted while you did that, you got the right number.
Well, that's what we can do here.
Here, we're taking one away from B. So if at the same time,
we just add one to A and produced that as our result, then that will work.
Because B is going to get smaller and smaller and smaller.
Each time B gets smaller by one, A will get bigger by one.
Eventually, B will be zero and A will be the sum.
So this is addition of two numbers together one at a time.
Let's try it.
It works.
I'll give you a little exercise to do now.
If this is blowing your mind a little bit too much,
then you don't have to do it.
But you might have fun doing it.
Finish this.
And again, the suggestion I'll make to you
is when you get to the template stage, set up
the template on the second argument.
And go ahead and work through this and then restart the video.
Or if you don't work through it yourself, restart the video right away.
So here's my version of subtract.
I get two check expects.
Base case one is first.
Remember, I'm templating on B-- so zero for the second argument.
If you subtract two from two, you get two.
If you subtract two from six, you get four.
And subtract is a little different than add.
Let me just change how I formatted add here.
I'll break down on two lines.
The way add works is you add to A while you subtract from B. The way
subtract works is you keep taking one away from both A and B
until B gets to zero.
That's add and subtract.
Let's just look at them.
The test pass-- that's good.
Watch this-- add N2 and N3.
So that's adding two to three.
That's five-- one, two three, four, five exclamation marks.
Subtract seven, add two to N3.
Two plus three is Five.
Seven minus five is two.
There's two.
We're doing all this arithmetic without using any natural numbers that
were given to us by Doctor Racquet.
We're using our own natural numbers.
It's a little bit wacky.
But let me just quickly show you how far you can
go if you want to keep pushing on this.
Here, I've got the famous factorial function.
Right, factorial of zero is one and factorial of everything else
is the number times fact of one less than the number.
If you don't know factorial, remember-- I promise there'd be no math.
I promised there'd be no math.
So you can just ignore this little bit.
That's factorial written for these new natural numbers.
Zero is uppercase.
It's our special primitive.
Sub one is uppercase.
Fact is upper-cased.
Ah, but I'm calling times.
We don't actually have times.
So you could do times.
You could wish for times and then do it.
Let me just show you that this works.
Fact of zero is one.
Fact of three is six.
Fact of four is 24.
If you count them, there would be 24.
Fact of eight-- hm-- what's-- takes a long time to print.
Long, long time to print-- very long time to print out
this long list of exclamation marks.
So what's the moral of the story here?
The most important thing is to know when we design programs,
we come up with data definitions that represent information.
And we can take any data to represent any information we want.
Now, of course, the underlying hardware makes some primitive data faster
than other primitive data.
We still haven't finished printing out this representation of fact of eight.
This is a terrible representation of natural numbers.
You would never want to use this.
I just wanted you to see that you can take the bottom
to be anything you want.
You can come up with your own numbers.
You can come up with your own strings.
You can come up with your own lists.
You can create any data you want.
So as I said at the beginning, that's a little wacky.
Most of the time-- nearly all the time-- you're
just going to work with whatever representation of numbers
the programming language gives you.
Still, it's kind of fun to explore that.
And remember, the rest of the material this week is not wacky.
The rest of the material this week is essential.
Representing arbitrary size information, well formed self
referential type comments, operating on lists and the reference rule--
all of that's essential material.
So be sure to practice it a lot and we'll see you again next week.