GREGOR KICZALES: Now I'm going to finish the first version of the Cat program.
That's going to involve designing two functions.
So in that way, it's going to be quite familiar.
We'll go through the HtDF recipe twice.
But we're going to be designing those functions in the context of a partially
complete larger program.
That's something that gets to be more and more important as we go forward.
As the programs get bigger, we often have lots of incomplete functions
that we need to finish before we're done.
And the most important thing in this video
is going to be how to use the Wishlist mechanism to keep track
of that work that remains to be done.
We have a constants part of the file, which we know corresponds
to the constants part of the analysis.
We have a data definitions part of the file that includes a world state
type, Cat, which we know corresponds to the changing information
part of the analysis.
We have a main function that calls big-bang
with two options, on-tick and to-draw.
Now, if we've forgotten exactly what we have to do,
I'll just search for three exclamation marks.
And very quickly, I see exactly what I have to do.
And if this program was larger, I could go here and say, show program contour.
And I'd see off to the right a picture of the whole program.
And you can barely see it there, but the places
where the search has found three exclamation marks are highlighted.
So if I had a very big program, I could go over here and quickly
jump to those places like that.
I'll hide that for now because we don't have that big a program.
So now what do I have to do?
Well, this tells me, hey, you're partway through an HtDF problem.
Here's the problem.
You've got a function that consumes a Cat and produces a Cat.
This is an HtDF problem consuming Cat.
It consumes Cat, produces Cat, produces the next cat
by advancing it one pixel to the right.
If I'm a little bit unsure about what a Cat is,
I can scroll up here to the data definitions
and see, oh, a cat is number, and here are some good examples.
And it's interpreted as the exposition of the cat in screen coordinates.
OK well, signature purpose, stub.
The next step is examples.
Let's see what's a good first example.
We'll say check expect advance-cat of, I don't know, three.
And we advance it by one pixel to the right.
So that should produce four.
And let's see.
This function behaves consistently independent of the number we get it.
So I really should only need one test.
I'll run the test to make sure that they're well-formed.
The test is running but failing, so it's well-formed.
This was the stub.
I'll comment it out.
I'll say, use template from Cat.
I'll go up here and get the template.
I'll copy it.
I'll just label this as being the stub.
I rename this to advance-cat, and let's see.
I've got to fill in the dots.
I advance it one pixel to the right.
Oh, this is just plus c 1.
Or if you want, there happens to be a function called add1.
We could just use that.
But I'll just say plus c 1.
Now I'll run again.
My test passed.
So let's see, I've done that piece of the wishlist.
I go back again looking for three exclamation marks.
Here's another function.
It consumes Cat and produces Image.
And it's supposed to render the cat image at an appropriate place on MTS.
And now I say to myself, well, what's the cat image?
I'll look up in the constants.
Oh yeah, there's a thing called CAT_IMAGE.
And I'll say to myself, well, what's the appropriate place?
I'll go look at the cat data definition.
Cat is number, so cat itself is a number.
And I interpret that as the x position.
So I've got the x position.
And I remember now that the y position doesn't change,
so I'll look in the constants for it too.
There it is, CTR-Y. So now I've got a pretty good idea
about how this is going to work.
Signature purpose stub, the next thing is examples.
So check expect, render of some cat.
Let's say 4.
What's that supposed to produce?
So render 4 does what?
Well, there is this primitive called place-image.
And what we need to do is we need to take the image of the cat, which
is cat image.
We need to put it at a certain xy location, which is 4 and CTR-Y.
And the background that we're going to put it on is MTS.
Now, I wrote that quickly because I remember exactly how place-image works.
If it takes you longer to write the expected result for a render function,
don't worry about that at all.
You're figuring out how the image functions
work, what you're going to use in order to produce the image you want.
Time spent here on this example translates
into time saved when you do the actual function.
So let me run this.
And we have a failing test, which is what we'd expect.
One thing that's nice to do with these render functions
is actually look at the failing tests.
Let's see.
We're getting an empty scene, because the stub always
produces the empty scene.
But what's useful to do-- let me just make
this bigger-- is to look at the expected result and see if our test makes sense.
That seems about right.
We've got a cat there that's nose is a little bit off the edge.
Remember, place-image places the center of cat image--
in other words, the center of this cat-- at the specified position.
So it's putting the center of the cat at 4
and CTR-Y. The CTR-Y part is definitely right.
And as I said, because the nose is a little bit off
and I can see the beginning of that eye, I think it is about 4.
So that seems about right.
We'll know for sure soon.
OK, let's see.
Let's finish up.
This is the stub.
We're going to use the template from cat.
Let's go get that template.
We'll rename this to render.
And let's see.
We need to render the cat image in an appropriate place on MTS.
Cat is itself the x-coordinate.
So looking at the signature, the purpose, and the example,
what I can see is that this is place-image cat image.
c is itself, the x-coordinate, CTR-Y and MTS.
I'll run that.
Both my tests are passing.
And now what I'd like to do is actually run the World program.
So going back to main, I can call main.
And the initial world state is whatever cat I give it,
whatever x-coordinate I give it.
So it probably makes sense to maybe call it with 0 to start.
So I run the program, and then I get this interaction window down here.
And I go main of 0, and there's my cat walking across the screen.
And now that I have a clear sense in my mind of what's a good default way
to start this program, what I'm going to do is go back to the main function
and say, start the world with main of 0, just as a way of telling
people what's a good way to start it.
I actually could have put in that start the world with main 0 at the beginning,
because as soon as we knew what the cat data definition was,
we knew that 0 would be a good default value.
I just waited to the end here.
So there we go.
We've got a complete, running world program.
One of things I hope you saw here is that by working systematically,
at any moment in time, our work was very focused.
Even though we did a lot, at every moment in time,
we were only doing one thing.
That's what working systematically did for us.
So when we were working on the domain analysis,
even then there were parts of it.
We worked on the constant information, then we did the changing information.
Then we did the big bang options, and that gave us the domain analysis.
As we started building the program, first we did the constants,
then we did the data definition for changing information.
Then we set up the main function and the wishlist
for our big bang option handlers.
And then we worked that wishlist one function at a time.
This is really important as programs get big.
And remember, programs get big.
Cars have millions of lines of code in them.
The big benefit of having a systematic process
is it lets you work on one thing at a time
and know that it's all going to work out.
Because in this case, when we were done and we said main of 0, bang.
We got a running world program.
And also let me repeat a point I made earlier about templates.
Because we have a process, some parts of the work we do
don't really necessarily end up as specific sub-parts
of the final program.
So the domain analysis itself isn't in the program.
It's something we wrote on a piece of paper.
But it was part of the process that got us there.
That's just like the template.
The template kind of disappears into the final function definition,
but the template is part of the process.
It gets us there.
People who design design methods, so that's
a kind of meta-design, that's one of the things they work on
is, how can there be elements of the design that
get you there even though they disappear in the final artifact?
We'll talk more about that as we go along.