GREGOR KICZALES: So now I'm going to work through a few design
problems involving lists.
As always, when I work through these problems,
there is going to be some parts of it that are pretty familiar, things
that you'll already know how to do.
And then there will be parts that are about the new list material.
So what I recommend you do and in fact, I've
said this before, I always recommend you do this, is get the starter file
and work through it with me.
And now, in these problems, you might even try stopping the video for a bit
and working ahead and then starting the video
and comparing what you did to what I did.
Again, that's always a good idea.
But don't worry about it if you get stuck and need to start the video.
After all, these are really the first list design
problems that I've asked you to do.
So you should expect it to take some time
to master this new part of the recipe.
There's a three-part problem here having to do with all the owls in the owlery.
First, there's a data definition problem where
we need to design a data definition to represent the weights of all the owls
and then we're going to design two functions that operate on that data.
As I go through this, and really whenever
you're working on a design problem, you should have a copy of the design
recipe pages opened up and maybe off to the side
next to your Dr. Racket window.
So let me start first by dividing my file
into two parts, one part for data definitions
and one part for the functions.
And now let's get to the data definition.
Let's see, we're going to represent the weight of all the owls in the owlery.
We don't know how many owls there's going to be,
so we need arbitrary size data, so we need
a well-formed, self-referential data definition.
Here we go.
Listed number is one of either empty because that's the base case or conds
number on list of number.
That's the self-reference case there.
For the interpretation, we'll say that each number in the list
is an owl weight and with numbers, it's always good to say the units,
so we'll say that's it's an owl weight in ounces.
And let's see, we'll have a couple of examples.
In one example, we always put the base case example first
in the data examples, so we'll say LON 1 is empty and LON 2, I don't know,
let's make it 2 LON and one owl will weigh 60 ounces
and the other owl will weigh 42 ounces.
Now, we'll do the template, fun for LON.
Let's see, the first rule is one of because there's two cases,
so that gets us a cond with two cases.
The second rule is atomic distinct for empty,
so that gets us the empty question mark predicated
and dot, dot, dot in the answer.
Next we've got compound because the conds is a compound.
It's a conds of a number, which is each element
of the list is a number and list of number, which is the self reference.
So in the template, we take apart the conds.
First of LON is just number, but rest of LON
is self referenced, so the self reference rule comes in.
And we wrap rest of LON into a natural recursion
we call to the very same template function.
We run it, there's no errors, so it's well formed.
We comment out the template.
There we go.
We've got the complete data definition.
And again, because there's arbitrary size information,
we need arbitrary size data, so there's a well-formed, self referential, tight
comment and a natural recursion in the template.
Now, let's go design the functions.
Let's see, the first function is going to consume the weights of some owls
and produced the total weight of all those owls.
So let's see.
It's going to consume list of number because that's the type that we're
using to represent the weights of an arbitrary number of owls
and it's going to produce, well, the weight of a number of owls
is the sum of a bunch of numbers, so that's number.
Produce total weight of owls in consumed list.
So we take a bunch of owls, we produce the total weight.
The stub is defined, let's call this function sumLON
and this stub will just produced 0.
We'll call that the stub.
Now, let's produce some examples.
There's a rule that for functions operating on arbitrary-size data,
the base case example should be first, so let's do that.
Check expect sum of empty, well, the sum of the weights
in an empty list of weights is 0.
Let's do another example.
We'll do an example with just a single owl in it.
So let's say the sum of maybe a list of owls that has this 160-ounce owl in it
is what?
Well, that's 60 and this might be a good place
to be a little bit more elaborate about it.
The reason it's 60 is because it's 60 plus the sum
of all the owls in the rest of the list, which in this case is empty.
So it's really 60 because it's 60 plus 0.
Let's do one more.
Sum of-- let's see conds 60, conds 42, and empty.
Well, what's that going to be?
Well, it's 60 plus the sum of the rest, which is 42,
plus the sum of its rest, which is 0.
You don't have to write that out like that, of course.
You could just write it like this because that's clearly what it is,
but by writing it the other way, I'm starting to think out in my mind,
well, how is this going to work?
I'm always going to add the first weight to the total all the other weights.
Let me run those examples.
They're well formed.
I'll go and get the template.
I bring the template down.
I comment out the stub.
I rename the template and I'm especially careful to rename
the natural recursion.
Now, let's see.
The sum of an empty list of weights is 0, otherwise,
the sum of another list of weights, it looks like it
whatever the first weight is plus the sum of the remaining weights
or the sum of the rest of the list.
So that's the first weight right there in this first example, for example.
That's going to be 60.
And again, in this first example here, that whole natural recursion
is going to be 0, so now, I know what goes here.
I just add these together.
I add the first weight to the sum of the remaining weights.
Let me get rid of these notes now.
All tests pass.
Notice what I did is I trusted the natural recursion
and I used the examples to help me think about what
I did with the first item of the list and what
I did with the result of the natural recursion.
I don't ever let myself think about what I'm
going to do with the rest of the list.
What I think about is what am I going to do
with the result of the natural recursion.
So there's that function done.
Let's now do the second function, which is
design a function that consumes the weights of owls
and produces the total number of owls.
So let's see.
The signature is, it consumes the weight of an arbitrary number of owls,
so that's represented as list of number.
And it produces how many weights there are in the list,
or how many owls are represented.
Well, that's not number.
That's a natural number because it's 0, 1, or 2.
It's something like that.
So that's natural.
Reduce total number of weights in consumed list.
We'll call this function count.
There's the stub.
Now, let's do examples.
Again, there's a rule that the base case should be first, so check expect,
count.
If I count the number of weights in an empty list of weights, that 0.
Now, let's see.
I can use the same examples as I used last time or different ones.
Let's use different ones, check, expect count, conds 12, empty.
Well, how many weights are there in that list?
Well, there's just one, so I could just write 1
or I can remind myself that the reason there's one
is because there's one for the first weight in the list, the 12,
and then there is 0 for the weights in the rest.
So I could write it like that.
Let's see.
Check, expect, count, conds 35, conds 12,
empty, and here there is one for the 35 and then
there's whatever is in the rest, which we already know is plus 1 and 0.
I could write that like that.
I'll run it and my tests are well formed.
So let me go get the template.
I will copy the template down.
Let me give myself a little more room to work here.
I'll copy the template down, I'll comment out the stub
and then I'll rename the template and the natural recursion.
Now, let's see.
If I'm trying to count how many weights there are in an empty list of weights,
well, that test and just intuition tells me that's 0.
And now, I'm trying to count the weights in a list that
actually has elements in it.
Well, the first weight, I don't really care what the first weight is.
I just am counting the fact there is a weight.
So that's going to be replaced by just one.
That's what this is telling me here.
In sum, we use the actual weight, so that stayed as first in LON.
But in count, we're not using the actual weight,
we're just using the existence of the weight.
So we're going to put a 1 there.
And now, I'm going to deliberately make a mistake
because I want to show you something about the two long lists row.
The mistake I'm going to make here is just
make this be plus 1 and then I'll look at this
and incorrectly decide to throw away the natural recursion and just put 0.
And now I'll run it and when I run it, this test is passing.
It's only the test that's too long that's failing
and that's why we have that rule about having a test for lists that
are too long because if you make a mistake throwing out
the natural recursion, then you're one long tests will often run properly.
So now, let me go back and pretend I didn't make that mistake.
I'll close this.
I'll just back up a little bit to where I was about to make that mistake.
Here I was.
And now I say to myself, well, I add 1 to-- and now what do I do?
I trust the natural recursion.
The natural recursion will be the right answer for the rest of the list,
so I'm just going to trust it.
I add one to whatever it produces.
I run and all six tests pass.