GREGOR KICZALES: Here's another How to Design Functions problem.
And, again, it elaborates on the problem we saw before.
What I'm going to do in this problem is when I start out,
I'm not going to choose the best signature.
And then we'll fix it later.
And the reason I'm doing that is I want to illustrate to you that the
How to Design Functions recipe is not intended to be
what's called a waterfall process.
It's not intended to be something that you do the first step and then
the second step and then the third step and absolutely get each step right.
It happens pretty often that you go through the recipe
and you get to the third or fourth step and maybe you realize;
oh, the signature's not exactly right.
And you go back and fix it.
And sometimes what even happens is you skip a first step
to go to a later step just to get started.
A common example is you're not quite sure about the signature
so you go write some examples and then you come back and do the signature.
Now, what I don't want to do is give you carte blanche
to jump immediately to the function definition and do that;
that's not going to be what we're going to call systematic design.
But I also don't want you to feel like; gee, I just
don't know what the signature is but I'm not allowed
to do anything else until I write it.
There is some flexibility in following the steps of the process.
It's a structured process, but it's not a locked-in waterfall process.
So here we go, let's do this example.
In this problem we're going to design a function called
image area that consumes an image and produces the area of that image.
And it says for area we just need to multiply
the image's width by its height.
So, let's see, this function consumes an image
and it produces the area of the image.
Now, you might think this should be number,
and that's actually going to turn out not to be right.
But I'm going to go ahead and pretend that I put number
for now because one of things I want to show
is that sometimes you realize part way through the process
that a piece of what you did before isn't right,
so I'm just going to put number for now.
I'm going to say produce image's width times height for area.
Let's see, the stub is going to be define image area.
I like to abbreviate image to img, and a good dummy value
is 0 because it's a number.
Now, let's do some examples.
Check-expect image-area of let's say I have
a rectangle that's 2 wide and 3 high and then it's just red.
What's the area of that?
Well, the area of that is times 2 3.
Let's run that test to see if it's well-formed.
Uh-oh, rectangle is not defined.
Oh, that's because whenever we use image functions,
we need to tell DrRacket that we want to use the image function.
And I forgot to do that.
So we're going to say require 2htdp/image
This is a very common mistake and I made it here
on purpose so that you would see it happen,
you just forget to do the require.
Now that we've done the require, the test is actually running and failing,
but it's running so we're doing reasonably well.
Let's keep going here to find image-area So that's the stub,
we'll label it as that.
We'll do the template, which will be . . .
img.
Now we'll make a copy of the template.
We'll comment out the original template and label it.
And now what's this going to be, it's got to be the image's width.
We're going to use image twice because we need its width and its height.
So we're going to use image twice.
We're going to say image-width of the image and image-height of the image,
and we're going to multiply those two together.
Let's run that.
And the test passed.
But now we might realize this interesting thing,
which is that images are always sized in pixels.
And pixels are always a natural number; 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, something like that.
You can't have 3.2 pixels, that's not how pixels are.
So if the width is always going to be a natural
and the height is always going to be a natural and you multiply those two,
this actually could be natural instead of number.
And one of things we're going to talk about a lot in the course
is that when you write the signature for a function,
you always want to use the most specific types that are correct.
Turns out it makes it much easier to think about using the function
and to debug programs if you use the most specific correct type.
So, in this case, this function was never
going to produce a floating point number, like 3.2.
It's always going to produce a natural, so we take the trouble
to make the signatures say that.
I'll save that file and run it one last time.
The test passed.