GREGOR KICZALES: So far we've seen several different types
of data-- primitive, interval, enumeration, itemization.
But all of them have been what's called atomic.
In each case a single data value really consists of just one value.
But lots of times we want to represent different kinds
of information-- information where two or more values naturally
belong together.
So for example, we might want to represent the xy position
of an object moving on the screen.
Or you might want to represent the first and last name of a single person.
We might want to represent the name, supervisor, and salary of an employee.
In all those cases there's two or more pieces of information
that naturally belong together.
To do that we're going to need compound data.
And we're going to cover compound data in three videos in a now-familiar form.
In this video we'll learn a basic mechanism called define-struct that
allows us to create compound values.
In the next video we'll learn how to update the how to design data
recipe for compound data.
And in the third video we'll see that the
how to design worlds recipe works pretty much unchanged for compound data.
And we'll make our most elaborate world program yet.
What we're learning is a new kind of definition called define-struct.
So here I'm going to define a struct, or a structure,
and I'm just going to call this one pos, as an abbreviation for position.
So that's the structure name.
And what comes next is something called the field names.
In this particular structure, I'll say that the fields are x and y.
So you can see I'm making a structure that's going
to help me represent xy positions.
Now when I write that definition, if I run it,
I don't get any value back because define-struct
is a definition just like the defines we've seen so far functioning
constant definitions.
It doesn't produce a value.
It just declares definitions.
In this case it declares four definitions.
The first one is a thing called a constructor, and it works like this.
I can say make-pos of 3 and 6.
And what that does is it produces a position
structure for which the value of the x field is 3 and the value of the y field
is 6.
That's an ordinary value, so I can do something
like make it be the value of a constant like P1.
And if I run that, now P1 is a constant, and if I go down here
and I just look at P1, DrRacket is going to show it to me.
Or I should say, the BSL language is going
to show it to me in the form of a call to the constructor-- make-pos 3 6,
in this case.
So that lets me put 3 and 6 together into a pos structure.
How do I then take them back apart?
Well before I show you that, let me just quickly do another example.
And now I'll show you how they come back apart.
The way they come back apart is that this define-struct also
defined two selectors.
One of the selectors is called pos-x.
And if I say pos-x of P1, then-- well, I get 3.
Because P1 is the make-pos 3 6, and so the x field of that is 3.
So pos-x of P1 is 3, and unsurprisingly, pos-y of P2 is 8.
So this produces 3, and this produces 8.
So make-pos is the constructor, pos-x and pos-y are the selectors,
and there's one more function that define-struct defines
for me-- a thing called the predicate.
It in this case is called pos?
And if I say pos?
of P1, I get true.
of some value that isn't produced by make-pos, like hello,
that gives me false.
So this is true and that's false.
So just to review quickly.
The way to form a define-struct is (define-struct some name,
which is going to be the name of the structure, a parenthesis,
and then some number of other names-- one or more--
that's the name of the fields.
That definition sets up a constructor which is always
called make dash the structure name.
It sets up as many selectors as there are
fields, which are always called the structure name dash the field name.
And it sets up a predicate which is always called structure name question
mark.
So that's the basic define-struct mechanism.
In the next video we're going to look at how to design compound data
definitions-- in other words, data definitions for compound data--
and they're going to use define-struct as a supporting mechanism.