GREGOR KICZALES: We've been learning about different kinds of values.
Numbers, strings, and images, and how to write expressions
that operate on those values.
In this video we're going to look at something quite different.
We're going to look at how to write constant definitions to give names
to values so that we can use those values
in different parts of the program.
Constant definitions are more than just a convenience.
We're going to see later in the course that they
help us make programs that are easy for other people
to read and easy for other people to change,
and that those two properties-- readability and changeabiliy--
are two of the most important properties a program can have.
But for now we're just going to focus on the mechanism of constant definitions
so that you can learn how to write a constant definition to give names
to a value that you use in other parts of the program.
So let's imagine that we're working on a program in which there's
a simple interactive game running in a window.
One thing we might want to do is give names
to the width and height of the window.
And the way we do that is we write open paren, define, and then
some name-- which we often put the names of constants in upper case like this--
and we might say that the window is 400 pixels wide.
And maybe the window is 600 high.
And that's two named constants.
If we run this program just like this we don't get any values out
because defining a constant doesn't produce a value.
But now what I can do is I can write an expression like this
and what happens is when DrRacket evaluates this, when it comes
to evaluating the name of a defined constant,
it's just going to use the constant's value there.
So this will become 400.
So the evaluation steps here would be times WIDTH will become 400.
That's the first evaluation step.
In the next evaluation step, HEIGHT will evaluate to 600.
At this point, all the arguments to times are values.
So now we'd have 240,000.
So the way to form a constant definition is
to have an open parenthesis, the word define, a space and then a name.
And names typically include letters of the alphabet in upper and lowercase.
They can also include numerical digits.
And in the beginning student language, they
can include lots of other characters like exclamation mark and question
mark and equals and things like that.
Some languages are more restrictive about that,
but the beginning student language is fairly generous about that.
You can't use parentheses or quotes of any kind, though.
The rules for evaluating a constant definition
are when Racket encounters the constant definition, it evaluates the expression
and uses the resulting value as the value of the name constant
going forward.
When evaluation encounters a name constant,
the name constant simply evaluates to the value
that the define associated with it.
Let's look at another example.
Let me get rid of all this now.
Suppose in this same program, in my game program,
what we have is the image of a cat going back and forth across the screen.
Well, I might want to give a name to that image
so that I can use it in lots of places.
So there's the cat.
And what I'm going to do here is go to the second edition
of the How to Design Programs book which we
use as the basis for the material in this course.
And they happen to have a little cat here that we're going to use.
So I'm just going to go copy this image.
And I'll come back over here and I'll just paste it right in here.
And what's happening in Racket is, remember, that images are values
and all values are expressions.
So I can stick that image right there in the program as an expression.
Most languages won't let you do this, but it's quite convenient
to be able to do it in BSL.
So we're going to take advantage of that.
So now I've got a cat and I could write some expressions.
So here rotate is a primitive and this says,
rotate the cat by minus 10 degrees.
Here's another expression that would rotate the cat by 10 degrees.
If we run this now, we see the first expression
produces the cat rotated this way.
The second expression produces the cat rotated that way.
And we might even want to give names to these.
Because remember, I said that we can have an expression
here after the constant name.
So now I've given names to those two rotated cats.
Oops.
I can't use those names.
I got to use different names.
You can only define a given constant name one time.
That's why it's called a constant name.
It can't change.
So I'll call those the RCAT and the LCAT.
And there they are.
So here see that what Racket is letting us do is say, define
and a name and then an expression.
That expression gets evaluated, and for evermore that value
will be associated with the constant name.
So we can use it in other places in the program.