GREGOR KICZALES: Now, I've completed a little bit of constant analysis
and defining some constants.
And I should say first that if you didn't
see right away that defining constants was a good thing to do here,
that's completely fine.
Sometimes you identify constants up front,
sometimes you realize later that you'll need them.
If you didn't see that right away, that's fine.
Let me show you what I've done.
I'm in a different version of the file now, tuition graph, v1.
I added a required 2 HTTP image at the top
because I knew I was going to be doing some drawing.
I made it part of the file for constants.
And I said, you know, this font size here
that we're going to be drawing the name of the schools in,
that looks like a good constant.
By defining a constant for it, it'll be easier for me to change later.
And the font color, similarly, I made that black.
And I also realized that there would have to be kind of a scaling factor
because these tuitions are going to be numbers like $20,000.
And I'm pretty sure I don't want to make the graph 20,000 pixels high.
That's going to be kind of a very high graph,
it won't fit on the screen or the piece of paper or anything.
So I invented a constant that I'm calling the y-scale,
or I could have called it the y-scale factor or something,
but it's basically how much I'm going to divide the dollars by
to convert it to the height of the bar.
And I just guessed 1/200, maybe that will end up being right,
maybe it won't.
We'll see later.
The bars have to have a width.
I just guessed that 30 pixels would look good.
And the bars have to have a color.
I just guessed that light blue would look good.
Remember, the reason we give names to these constants
is to make it easy to get the program going quickly,
then you can adjust them to look a little bit better.
So that's the constants.
The next thing I have to do is the data definitions
for representing the information in this problem.
Remember the information that we have to represent
is for an arbitrary number of schools, we need to know for each school
what its name is and what its tuition is.
Now, what makes this problem different is
we're going to have two data definitions.
There's going to be one compound data definition called school.
And that's going to be used to represent information about an individual school.
And then there's going to be an arbitrary size data definition called
list of school, which will represent an arbitrary number of those school units.
And what's going to happen there is the second data definition, list of school,
is going to refer to the first data definition, school.
And that's going to carry through the entire problem.
So there'll be what's called a reference relationship in the type comment.
There'll be what's called a natural helper in the templates.
And in the final function, there'll be a helper function call.
We've seen this before.
It's a theme of this part of the course.
The structure of the information determines the structure of the data
determines the structure of the templates
determines the structure of the functions.
So now let's go look at how this plays out in the code.
I'm in tuition graph v2.
And I've started the data definition.
But I've saved the most interesting part to do now.
In terms of the compound information about the school that's
a compound data definition, like the ones we've seen before.
I defined a structure called school with two fields, name and intuition.
And I said that a school is a make school, where name
is a string and tuition is a natural.
And I'm just saying here that name is the school's name.
And tuition is the international student's tuition in US dollars.
Remember we like to put units for numbers in interpretations.
And I just decided on US dollars, you could use whatever currency you want.
And then I just put some examples.
I said school 1 is a school called school 1 that has a tuition of $27,797
and school 2 is $23,300 and school 3 is $28,500.
The template for school is straightforward.
It's compound of two fields.
Both fields are primitive types, string and natural.
So the template just ends up looking like that.
Now, the list of school data definition starts out just like we've seen before.
I'll say that list of school is one of either empty for the base
case, or cons something list of school for the self-reference case.
But the question is what's the something?
And for the something here rather than putting a primitive type,
I've put school.
Because that's what list of school really needs to be.
It needs to be a list of representations of schools.
So that in this list, I'll have an arbitrary number of schools.
And then for each school, I'll have its name and its tuition.
And so this type comment has something quite new.
And it's really the new thing in this whole problem.
In addition to the self-reference relationship,
it also has what we want to call a reference relationship.
It refers right here to a non-primitive type.
And the way we're going to draw that is with an arrow,
like the arrow we used for self-reference,
but we're going to label it with an r for reference.
That picture of the two type comments with the two arrows
is going to define the structure of the entire rest of this problem.
Let me show you how that starts happening in the template.
Define fn for los, los, template rules used.
And it starts out pretty normally.
I'll speed things up a bit here.
Now, here's where it gets a little bit different.
We've already seen in the previous examples that we know that rest of los
is going to be a value of type list of school.
And that's going to cause us to use the self-reference rule.
I'm going to skip a line here.
That's going to cause us to use the self-reference rule.
And the self-reference rule makes us put a natural recursion right here.
But remember, this type comment has a second arrow.
We know that the type of first los is going to be school.
And school is a non-primitive type, that's why we have the arrow labeled r.
And that's going to cause us to use what's called the reference rule.
And the reference rule says that first los is school,
it's a non-primitive type.
So what we're going to do right here, we're going to put in a call
to the template function for the referred to type.
That picture is a little hard to understand like that.
So let me just rearrange it a little bit.
And what I've done in this picture is I've
put the two type comments next to each other and the two templates
next to each other.
And I think that when I arrange it like this,
you could see what's going on here a little bit better.
In the two type comments, we have the self-reference from earlier this week.
And we have the reference, which we just saw today for the first time.
And in the templates, the self-reference produces a natural recursion.
And the reference produces what we're going to call a natural helper.
When we design a function that consumes a list of school,
we'll see what the presence of this natural helper in the template
does to the design of that function.