GREGOR KICZALES: The next three videos are
examples of designing a function that consumes non-primitive data, data
that's defined by your own data definition.
Now, they're HtDF problems, so mostly you know how to do them.
Remember, I said the HtDF recipe is largely orthogonal to the form of data.
But it isn't completely orthogonal to the form of data.
One real dependence between function design and form of data
has to do with the number of tests that's appropriate for that function.
So in these videos, I'm going to pay particular attention
to the number of tests that we're going to use, based on the form of data.
I'm in aisle-starter.rkt.
And the problem we're asked is to use the SeatNum data definition,
and design a function to produce is true if the given seat
number is on the aisle.
So the first thing I would do is go look at the seat num data definition,
and it reminds me that the SeatNum is a natural number from 1 to 32 inclusive,
and that it's seat numbers in a row, and 1 and 32 are the aisle seats.
So now I can get started on my function.
I'll quickly do the signature purpose and stub.
Let's see, it's going to consume a SeatNum.
And we're supposed to produce true when the sea number is on the aisle,
so that means it's going to produce a Boolean.
And it'll produce false when the seat number isn't on the aisle.
And let's see, produce true if the given seat number is on the aisle.
And let's see the function.
This is a predicate, so we'll name it using the naming convention
for predicates like this, aisle?
we'll have seat number is-- and we'll just produce false for the stub.
So let me run that, to make sure the stub is well formed.
And it is.
OK, now let's get to the examples.
Now here's the first place where the data definition is really
going to have something to say.
If we go back to the How to Design Data page,
and we go to the section on intervals and we go to the section on Guidance
on Examples and Test, it tells us that when
writing tests for functions operating on intervals,
we should be sure to test closed boundaries as well as midpoints,
and always be sure to include enough tests to check
all other points of variance.
So let's go back to the code.
I've got an interval with two closed endpoints.
So I know that what I'm going to need are three tests.
One for the first closed end point, which is 1.
One for the middle, which is-- middle doesn't
have to be the exact middle, something like the middle.
We'll call it 16.
And one for the closed upper end point, which is 32.
And now what are these going to be?
Well, I'm supposed to produce true if the given seat number is on the aisle.
Let's see, this one is on the aisle.
This one is not.
And this one is.
Notice how much information the data definition
gave me about generating the tests.
Data definitions are always going to be helpful this way.
They're not always going to make it quite this straightforward,
but data definitions, the structure of the data
definition, the structure of the data, tells us a lot about the tests we need.
So let me run that.
Good.
They're all running.
Now, for the template what I'm going to do
is I'm first going to comment out the stub.
I'm going to say use template from SeatNum, and I'll just leave that note.
I'll copy the template down, and I'll use it like that.
I have to rename it to be aisle?
because that's the name of this function.
And let's see.
I'm consuming a seat number, which is a natural from 1 to 32,
and I need to produce true if it's an aisle seat.
That means I need to produce true if seat num is 1, also seat num is 32.
And I just need to or those two together.
Let's try that.
All three tests pass.
So there you.
That's designing a function that consumes an interval.
And the big piece of help we got from knowing that's an interval
is well, of course we got the template, but we also
got the structure of the tests.
In this case, it's an interval with two closed ends.
So we have a test for each of the ends, and a test for somewhere in the middle.