GREGOR KICZALES: In this how to design data problem,
the type comment is going to end up with a one of, but not all of the subclasses
are going to be single distinct values.
So this is what's going to be called an itemization,
and it'll be the most complex form of data that we see this week.
This is the problem in Countdown Starter.
So what we're supposed to do here is design a data definition
to represent the current state of a New Year's Eve countdown.
So this is something like the countdown ball in Times Square.
And we're asked to design a data definition for that.
As always, when we designed a definition the first thing
is to clearly identify the information in the problem domain
that we're trying to represent.
And in this case, the problem statement makes that very clear to us.
In particular, it makes it clear that the information
falls into one of three categories.
The countdown hasn't started, it's from 10 to 1 seconds before midnight,
or it's complete.
The previous problem we saw, the letter grade problem,
also had three categories.
But here the categories are different.
This first one is kind of distinct.
The countdown hasn't started, that's a clear, distinct state.
But in this second category, there's not a single distinct value there.
There's 10, 9, 8, all the way to 1.
So there's a number of different values there.
And then in the third category, again there's a distinct state there,
the countdown is complete.
So this isn't going to be an enumeration.
This is going to be what's called an itemization, because there
are two or more subclasses, at least one of which
is not a single, distinct value.
This center one is not a single, distinct value.
So that's going to be an itemization.
And again, after this video is over, I encourage
you go to the Design Recipes page, go to the How to Design Data page.
This table would remind you that itemization
is what you need to use in a case like this,
and you can go ahead and read about the itemizations.
Do that carefully after this video is over, or work through the problem now.
So let's see.
We start with the Type Comment, as always.
So we'll say that Countdown is one of-- and there's three subclasses.
And now we have to decide for each subclass how we'll represent that,
what data will represent that.
Well, lets see.
If the countdown hasn't yet started, that's kind of a distinct state.
So we could use any piece of atomic, distinct data to represent that.
Let's just use False.
We'll only use the Boolean value False, to represent
that the countdown hasn't yet started.
Now in the second subclass, let's just say
that that'll be a natural number, from 1 to 10 inclusive.
And in the third case, we also need a distinct value there.
And we'll just use the string in this case, complete.
So now we've got three distinct subclasses
that correspond to the three distinct kinds of information that
need to be represented.
And we'll do an interpretation here.
And I'll use multiple lines for this interpretation.
I'll say false means countdown has not yet started.
Natural 1 to 10 means countdown is running, and how many seconds left.
And Complete means countdown is over.
And if you want to you, you can indulge your inner Virgo
and make these line up nicely.
And if you don't want to, you don't have to.
There's the Type Comment and the Interpretation.
Now we need some examples.
So we might say, define Countdown 1 is-- now, I'll put a false here.
It's an atomic distinct, so in some sense
you might find that that example is not particularly illustrative.
But maybe I'll have Countdown 2 is 10, and I could put a comma in here
if I want, just started running.
Define Countdown 3, almost over.
And define Countdown 4, complete.
And that one's clear.