GREGOR KICZALES: I hope you're already beginning
to see some of the power of working with a systematic design process.
One piece of that is that you always know what to do next.
There's always the next step of the recipe.
And that step of the recipe tells you what kind of thing you need to write
and where you should be looking to figure out how to write it.
So when it's time to write the examples, you
know that you can look at the signature and the purpose
to help you figure out what the examples need to be.
You've also seen the benefit of producing uniformly structured code.
Code that's easy for other programmers to read and code that
has an appropriate number of tests.
But in this next part, you're going to see the power of systematic design
really start to step up.
What's going to happen is that because the design method
itself, in other words, the meta design in some sense.
Because the design method itself is structured
so that the how to design functions recipe is orthogonal,
which is a $10 word for means mostly independent.
Because the functions recipe and the data recipe are orthogonal,
it means that as we learn more forms of data,
the functions recipe is going to continue to work unchanged or mostly
unchanged with those forms of data.
So now we're going to begin to cover the ground a lot
more quickly because of this property of the way the recipes are designed.
In week one and particularly at the end of week one,
we learned about primitive data, including
types like string, number, and image.
And we learned the how to design function recipe
and we used it to design functions like double,
which consumed a number, and yell, which consumed a string, and area, which
consumed a number.
And image area, which consumed an image.
Now, what started to happen this week is we've started
to learn about other forms of data.
And in particular, we've learned about non primitive data.
Data where there's a type that we design with the how to design data definitions
recipe.
And what we did in the last two videos was
we learned about atomic non primitive data and we designed the type CityName.
And then we designed the best function that consumed the CityName.
And earlier in the week, you actually saw a preview of a form of data
called enumerations, which we haven't explicitly covered yet.
We'll do that shortly.
But you saw another type called TrafficLightColor and a function
next-color.
Now, what's going to happen the rest of this week
is we're going to learn about some other forms of data,
including intervals, enumerations, itemizations, and a special form
called distinct.
And we'll see examples of those types.
And you'll be able to design functions that operate on them.
As I said before, the HtDF recipe is largely orthogonal to the form of data.
So HtDF works the same way with different forms of data.
And what that means in this week is we're
going to focus most of the lecture time on designing
different kinds of data definitions.
And we're going to have to spend much less time on designing
functions that consume that data.
In some sense, what's happening is we did this little piece of the y-axis,
how to design functions, and now we're working out the x-axis.
And all of this space in the middle, the cross product of the two axes,
comes very cheaply.
We won't have to spend much lecture time talking about these kinds of functions.
Instead, we spend most of the lecture time talking about forms of data
and designing these kinds of functions comes almost for free.
And what's great is the power of having a design
method in which the individual recipes are orthogonal to the form of data
is only going to grow from there.
Next week, we're mostly going to focus on two things.
One new form of data, compound data.
And also a recipe that helps us design interactive programs like games
and animations and things like that.
And again, because of this orthogonality, most of the lecture time
will be on compound data and on the how to design worlds recipe.
And we'll do some examples in the cross product,
some examples in the green box, but we won't have to do all of them
in lecture.
Because once you know how to design worlds and once you know compound data,
you can do anything in the blue, red, or green boxes.
Beyond that, when we do lists and trees, lists and trees
are complicated structures, but because of this orthogonality,
again, they're going to be much easier to learn in this course
than they are in some other courses.
Orthogonality is always great in design when you can get it.
Here, you've got orthogonality in the design of the actual design method.
And it's giving us some wonderful properties here.
We can learn HtDF and HtDW and we can learn forms of data
and we get the cross product for free.
That's going to be a big benefit in terms of using this method.
And later on in the course, we'll see some other examples
of where we work orthogonality into our own designs
and get some similar benefits.