GREGOR KICZALES: The key to solving complex design problems is
to break them down into smaller pieces.
Now, the recipes already do that, of course.
The data recipe breaks data design down into individual steps.
The function recipe does the same and so does the world recipe.
But sometimes we need more decomposition than that.
Sometimes we need to break a data representation
into multiple types or a function design into multiple functions.
Now, we've seen a couple examples of that already, of course.
Whenever we have the reference rule, then we
end up with a natural helper function, and the world's recipe also breaks
the design down into multiple handlers.
But this week, we're going to look at more examples of how
we break types and functions down into multiple types and multiple functions.