GREGOR KICZALES: So there's the data definition and two functions.
One function, next-cat, can take us from one cat to the next cat.
In other words, it can advance the cat's x position by three
each time, 0, 3, 6, and so on.
The other function can take us from a cat to an image of the cat,
in other words, the image of the cat at the appropriate position
on the background called MTS.
Now we need to understand how those two functions need
to dance together in order for the cat to move across the screen the way
we want it to.
Suppose the cat starts at 0.
We need to call render-cat to get the appropriate image and display that.
Then we need to call next-cat with 0 to get 3.
Then we need to call render-cat with 3 to get the image
and display it, then next-cat with 3 to get 6.
Then render-cat we call with 6 to get the next image and display that.
Then we call next-cat with 6 to get 9, then render-cat with 9 to get the image
and display it, next-cat with 9 to get 12, render-cat with 12,
next-cat with 12, 15, and so on and so on and so on.
And all we need to do is do that 28 times
a second, which I can't talk that fast.
To do that, to wire render-cat and next-cat together that way,
DrRacket gives us a special expression called a big-bang expression.
And here's an example of how we would use big-bang to make the cat walk.
The first argument to big-bang is an expression
that evaluates to what the big-bang calls the initial world
state, the initial state of this whole interactive world.
In this case, the state of the interactive world
is represented by the cat type, and so we're
going to give it an expression that produces a cat.
So 0 is the initial position of the cat.
After its first argument, big-bang takes a number of options.
And it takes so many that the way it does it is to take them by name.
That way you can give it only the options you want to give it each time.
The way to read this first option is it says,
each time the clock ticks, call the next-cat function,
pass it as an argument the current state of the world,
and it will give you back the next state of the world.
Because in this particular big-bang expression the state of the world
is represented by Cat, I've put a comment
here saying that the type of the first argument to big-bang, in this case,
is Cat.
And another comment here that says that the signature of the next-cat function
is that it consumes Cat and produces Cat.
The second option to big-bang, in this case, is called to-draw.
And you should read this use of to-draw as saying
that what big-bang's going to do is on each clock tick,
it's going to call render-cat, passing render-cat as its first argument
the current world state, in other words, a Cat.
And render-cat will produce an image, and big-bang will display that image.
And I've made a note here off to the side that the signature of render-cat
is that it consumes Cat and produces Image.
So what big-bang is doing for us is it's taking
all the little pieces of our world, the initial world state, the tick function,
the draw function, and it's combining all those pieces together
to get a world.
Do you see the joke behind the name now?
It squeezes the pieces together, big-bang, it produces a world.
Whether you like that joke about the name or not, that is the name.
I didn't come up with it.
One other point to make about big-bang is
that it's what computer scientists like to call polymorphic.
It can work for any type of world state.
So big-bang doesn't just work with cats.
It can work, for example, if you have an interactive world
program that has to do with fireworks, then the world state could be firework.
Or if you have an interactive program that has to do with lots of fireworks,
then the world state could be list of firework.
The world state can be anything you want to be.
So actually here, where we've noted cat and cat to cat and cat to image,
as far as big-bang's concerned it can be anything.
So really it could be X, X to X, and X to image.
All big-bang wants is for you to give it an initial world state.
And then for on-tick, you've got to give it
a function that consumes a world state of that type
and produces a world state of that type.
And then for to-draw, you have to give it
a function that consumes the world state of that type, whatever
it is, and produces image.
The key thing is, in any one use of big-bang,
all the X's have to be the same type.
They all have to be consistent.
That's what matters to big-bang.
So there's big-bang.
It's without a doubt the most complicated single primitive
we're going to use this term.
It's a user interface framework.
And user interface frameworks, in other words,
tools that integrate a bunch of functionality
together to get an entire user interface, user interface frameworks
are always somewhat complicated.
This one is simpler than most.
Don't worry about it.
We're going to spend the whole week on it.
You'll get a lot more chances at it.
But the basic thing to understand is this picture
up here in the upper right, that's what big-bang is doing.
It's starting with an initial world state,
and then it's coordinating, calling functions like render-cat and next-cat,
to produce the combined behavior of the interactive program
that we want to have.
We'll also see, starting in the next video, that there's more options.
So for example, big-bang has an option called on-key.
And you could imagine that the way that works is on-key wants a function,
then it will call when a key is pressed on the keyboard.
And that function should process the key properly and produce the next world
state.
What we'll also see in the next video is we're
going to introduce a design recipe for designing interactive programs using
big-bang.
And that design recipe is going to help make it a lot easier
to write programs that use big-bang.